<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eliza's babes or, the virgins-offering. Being divine poems, and meditations. Written by a lady, who onely desires to advance the glory of God, and not her own.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84367</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E535C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1289_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9323</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873524</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873524</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169720</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84367)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169720)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 173:E1289[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eliza's babes or, the virgins-offering. Being divine poems, and meditations. Written by a lady, who onely desires to advance the glory of God, and not her own.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 103, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for Laurence Blaiklock, and are to be sold at his shop neer the Middle-Temple Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169720:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ELIZA'S BABES: OR THE Virgins-Offering.</p>
            <p>BEING Divine
<list>
                  <item>Poems,</item>
                  <item>and</item>
                  <item>Meditations.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Written by a LADY, who onely deſires to advance the glory of GOD, and not her own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Laurence Blaiklock,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop neer the <hi>Middle-Temple</hi> Gate.</p>
            <p>1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:169720:2"/>
            <head>TO MY SISTERS.</head>
            <l>LOoke on theſe Babes as none of mine,</l>
            <l>For they were but brought forth by me;</l>
            <l>But look on them, as they are Divine,</l>
            <l>Proceeding from Divinity.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:169720:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen firſt the motion came into my minde, that theſe <hi>Babes</hi> of mine, ſhould be ſent into the world; I would faine have ſuppreſt that motion, for divers reaſons which may be imagined, by them, that ſhall read them: But eſpecially by thoſe, that knew my diſpoſition. But riſing one day, from my Devotions, it was ſuggeſted to my conſideration, that thoſe deſires were not given me, to be kept in private, to my ſelf, but for the good of others.</p>
            <p>And if any unlike a Chriſtian ſhall ſay; I wrote them, for mine owne glory. I like a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, will tell them; I therefore ſent them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; for ſuch a ſtrict union is there betwixt my deare God and mee, that his glory is mine, and mine is his; and I will tell them too, I am not aſham'd of their birth; for before I knew it, the Prince of eternall glory had affianced mee to himſelfe; and that is my glory.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169720:3"/>
            <p>And now to all ſuch ſhall I direct my ſpeech, whoſe brave ſpirits may carry them to high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires. Place not your affections in your Youth, beneath your ſelves; but if you would be happy on earth, and enjoy theſe outward bleſſings, with free and lawfull contentment; beſtow your firſt affections on my Almighty Prince. I would have you all love him, and him to love you all. I being his, muſt doe, as he will have mee: and methinks, hee directs me to tell you, that you ſhall never bee happy on Earth, nor glorious in Heaven, if you doe not love him, above all earthly things. More, I muſt tell you, that if you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> will dedicate to his ſervice, and preſent into his hands, your wealth, witt, ſpirit, youth, beauty, he will give you wealth, if leſſe, more uſefull: your witt more pure, your ſpirit more high, and tranſcendent, and your youth and beauty, which time will ſteale from you, or ſome malignant diſeaſe, with paine, rend from you; them he will lay up awhile for you, and returne them againe for eternity, with great advantage. And that you need not doubt of the certainety of what is told you, they that tell it you have found part of it true, and ſhall the reſt. I cannot be content, to be happy alone, I wiſh you all bleſſed too; nor can I ſmother up thoſe great and infinite bleſſings, that I have received from him, with private thankes. That Great Prince of Heaven and Earth, proclaimed by Angels, that he was come into the world, to ſhew
<pb facs="tcp:169720:3"/> his good will and love to mee; was here content, to dye a publique death for me, to ſave me, from a Hell of miſery; in which I lay, and ſhould have layen, had not he, the Prince of Peace, and the faireſt and chiefeſt among the ſons of men, ſhed his moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and royal blood, for mee; and before he dyed he left word, that I ſhould not feare, for it was his great and glorious Fathers will, to beſtow on us a Kingdome. And was ſo great a Prince, not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to avow ſo great affection and love to mee, and ſhall I be aſhamed to returne him publique thankes, for ſuch infinite and publique favours? No: I will not, but with all my minde, heart, and ſoule, I bleſſe and praiſe my Almighty God, for ſo great benefits, beſtowed on me, his unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſervant. Methinks it is not enough for my ſelf onely to doe it, but I muſt ſend out my <hi>Babes,</hi> to doe it, with mee, and for me: And if any ſhall ſay, others may be as thankefull as ſhee, though they talk not ſo much of it; Let them know that if they did rightly apprehend the infinite mercies of God to them, they could not be ſilent: And if they doe not thinke the mercies of God worth publique thankes; I doe, and therefore I will not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to be that one in ten that returned, to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge himſelfe a cleanſed Leaper. And now my <hi>Babes</hi> ſome may ſay to you, unleſſe you had been more curiouſly dreſt, or more finely ſhap'd, your Mother might have kept you in obſcurity. Tell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem, I ſent you to their more learned and refined
<pb facs="tcp:169720:4"/> wits, to forme you to a more curious ſhape, and tyre you in a more inticing dreſs. But this I will ſay for you, You want none of your limbs, and your cloaths are of rich materials. I dare not ſay, I am loth to let you goe: Go you muſt, to praiſe him, that gave you me. And more Ile ſay for you, which few Mothers can, you were obtained by vertue, borne with eaſe and pleaſure, and will live to my content and felicity. And ſo Adieu: But ſtay! Something you may truly ſay for your own imperfections, and your Mothers excuſe, That ſome of you were borne, when herſelf was but a child; but</p>
            <lg>
               <l>My joy, my bliſſe, my happy Story</l>
               <l>In Heaven is writ, and that's my Glory.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169720:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſalme 56. Verſ. 10.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Glory in the word of God,</l>
                     <l>To praiſe it I accord.</l>
                     <l>With joy I will declare abroad,</l>
                     <l>The goodneſs of the Lord.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All you that goodneſs doe disdaine,</l>
                     <l>Goe; read not here:</l>
                     <l>And if you doe; I tell you plaine,</l>
                     <l>I doe not care.</l>
                     <l>For why? above your reach my ſoule is plac'ſt,</l>
                     <l>And your odd words ſhall not my minde diſtaſte.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>And when you read theſe lines, miſtake not a Divine affection, for a Poeticall fancy; for I affect not to expreſs my fancy, but I would have my fancy expreſs my affection.</p>
            <div type="poems">
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Invocation.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Come Sacred Muſe to mee this day,</l>
                     <l>And ever here, make you a ſtay</l>
                     <l>Within the cloſet of my breſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>For I with thee, doe finde great reſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>My ſweet Companion, here thou art,</l>
                     <l>Dear Lord, Let it not from me part.</l>
                     <l>From thee, this gift, I did receive,</l>
                     <l>To thee, the ſame I doe bequeath.</l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:169720:5"/>
                     <l>Aſpire, aſpire, my minde, aſpire,</l>
                     <l>From earthly things unto the higher.</l>
                     <l>Set not thy minde on baſe deſires,</l>
                     <l>But thinke upon the heavenly Quires,</l>
                     <l>Of Angels ſweet, that ſinging be,</l>
                     <l>And ſtill the face of God doe ſee.</l>
                     <l>Admiring much, his wiſedome great,</l>
                     <l>And glorious ſweetneſſe of his ſeat.</l>
                     <l>Then hie my Soule to that ſweet place,</l>
                     <l>Where glory is, with mirth and grace.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Requeſt.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Come ſweet Spirit expell my feare,</l>
                     <l>Aſſure me that thou haſt a care</l>
                     <l>Of me, and of my giddy youth,</l>
                     <l>Aſſure me of it, ſtill for Truth,</l>
                     <l>That thy Spirit ſhall me direct,</l>
                     <l>And that thy power ſhall me protect.</l>
                     <l>Then ſhall my ſpirit be at reſt,</l>
                     <l>And with ſweet thoughts my ſoule be bleſt;</l>
                     <l>When that I know, thou loveſt me,</l>
                     <l>And that my youth ſhall guided be,</l>
                     <l>By that Spirit, that doth diſpoſe,</l>
                     <l>All for the happineſſe of thoſe,</l>
                     <l>The which be ſervants unto thee;</l>
                     <l>Bleſt be thy Name, that ſo made mee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Anſwer.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HIs Spirit much thou doſt deſire,</l>
                     <l>His Spirit much he will inſpire.</l>
                     <l>What thou deſireſt, that ſhall be,</l>
                     <l>Thou haſt thy wiſhes granted thee.</l>
                     <l>With thee, needs muſt I wiſh to live,</l>
                     <l>That mak'ſt me wiſh what t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ou wilt give.</l>
                     <l>Lord harden thou my heart, as hard as ſteel,</l>
                     <l>And loves vaine paſſion, let me never ſeel,</l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:169720:5"/>
                     <l>Onely in Heaven, my ſoul ſhall ſeek her reſt,</l>
                     <l>In Heaven perpetually to be bleſt.</l>
                     <l>On Earth a while I muſt tormented be,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe that ſin, too much abides in me.</l>
                     <l>It is the injoying of thy Spirit,</l>
                     <l>That makes my ſoule here, true joy inherit.</l>
                     <l>And here to ſhew me that thou hat'ſt my ſin</l>
                     <l>Thy Spirit like the Sun-beams, is drawn in.</l>
                     <l>Then doth my Soul, full wo, and ſad remaine</l>
                     <l>Till that ſweet ſpirit doth appeare againe.</l>
                     <l>Then when thy Spirit, againe reigns in me</l>
                     <l>Then comes my joy, away my paine doth flee.</l>
                     <l>For when thy Spirit my Soul doth injoy,</l>
                     <l>Nothing can then, my happy Soul annoy.</l>
                     <l>For why? No cauſe of ſorrow, I can ſee,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe, beyond my ſelfe, it raiſeth me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Anguiſh.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>FRom this diſtraction, Lord my poor ſoul bring,</l>
                     <l>That ſtill thy heavenly prayſes, I may ſing.</l>
                     <l>For this diſtemper doth my ſoul affright;</l>
                     <l>My Lord, it takes from me, all my delight,</l>
                     <l>And pleaſure that I had, in ſerving thee.</l>
                     <l>This trouble great, vaine folly brings to me.</l>
                     <l>If from thy holy ſervice, I be tane,</l>
                     <l>No comfort can I find, but endleſſe paine.</l>
                     <l>For what can yeeld our Souls here true content,</l>
                     <l>If to ſerve thee, we are not wholly bent?</l>
                     <l>For here I ſee vaine pleaſures, quickly fly,</l>
                     <l>And that which I did love, muſt ſurely dye.</l>
                     <l>But in thy ſervice, if I pleaſure take,</l>
                     <l>And thy ſweet word my whole delight do make.</l>
                     <l>That word doth ſtill my drooping ſoul aſſure,</l>
                     <l>That for the beſt it ſhall be all to me,</l>
                     <l>If patiently I doe awaite on thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:169720:6"/>
                  <head>Of Submiſſion.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHat comes to me, Lord comes from thee?</l>
                     <l>Nought comes to me, but comes from thee.</l>
                     <l>What though, againſt my will it be,</l>
                     <l>If thou it fitting ſeeſt for me.</l>
                     <l>Let be, and Maſter thou my will,</l>
                     <l>That I thy ſervant, may fulfill</l>
                     <l>Thy holy will, and thee obey:</l>
                     <l>Make me obedient be, I pray.</l>
                     <l>If I obey thy Majeſty,</l>
                     <l>I need not fear, although I dye.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Hope.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHat though my morning be debard of light,</l>
                     <l>For me thou ſhalt break forth, a noon moſt bright.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The onely Comforter.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHat in this world doe I deerer eſteem?</l>
                     <l>Or greater in my minde, here ſtill do deem?</l>
                     <l>Then that Spirit which floweth ſtill from thee,</l>
                     <l>Which makes my ſoule in happy bliſſe to be?</l>
                     <l>For nothing in this world, here can me pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>Nor yet my Soule, from paine and grief can eaſe:</l>
                     <l>But thy ſweet ſpirit which abides for aye,</l>
                     <l>For theſe vaine worldly things, doe fade away.</l>
                     <l>My ſoul immortall, did proceed from thee,</l>
                     <l>And pleas'd with mortall things, ſhe cannot bee.</l>
                     <l>You earthly pleaſures, I can uſe you all,</l>
                     <l>But treaſures of my ſoule, Ile not you call.</l>
                     <l>Goe flee vaine pleaſures, for ſure all muſt grant,</l>
                     <l>Nought can us pleaſe, but what is permanent.</l>
                     <l>In thee my Lord, my ſoul alone is bleſt,</l>
                     <l>In thee alone, I doe attaine ſweet reſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:169720:6"/>
                  <head>The Soules Flight.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHither away, my Soule, do'ſt high,</l>
                     <l>That thou ſo fain, from me would'ſt fly?</l>
                     <l>Sure it is, to ſome holy place;</l>
                     <l>That thou thy ſelfe, there may'ſt ſolace.</l>
                     <l>Thou wilt not here abide with me,</l>
                     <l>But goe to God, there to be free.</l>
                     <l>To him thou liv'ſt, to him thou flyeſt,</l>
                     <l>That is the reaſon that thou higheſt.</l>
                     <l>And here I wiſh thee not to ſtay,</l>
                     <l>I wiſh to Heaven, thou mighſt away.</l>
                     <l>From Priſon oft, I wiſh thee free,</l>
                     <l>That thou mayſt be at liberty.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Virgins Offring.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WIth thee, bleſt Virgin, I would bring</l>
                     <l>An Offering, to pleaſe my King.</l>
                     <l>Two Turtle Doves, thou didſt preſent,</l>
                     <l>Can there be better by me ſent.</l>
                     <l>A Lambe more pure, then they could be,</l>
                     <l>I heard was thither brought by thee.</l>
                     <l>Theſe two ſmall Turtles now of mine,</l>
                     <l>To him, I do preſent with thine.</l>
                     <l>The Lambe will ſerve for thee and mee,</l>
                     <l>No better offering, can there be.</l>
                     <l>Thus with thee, Virgin doe I bring</l>
                     <l>An offering will pleaſe my King.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>To my Doves.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>YOur life, I ment not, till my death</l>
                     <l>Might give you freedome with my breath.</l>
                     <l>And when I breath'd in Heavens Aire free,</l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:169720:7"/>
                     <l>I did intend your libertie,</l>
                     <l>But offer'd now, you ſure muſt be,</l>
                     <l>A Sacrifice of thanks from mee.</l>
                     <l>When we are dead, we cannot give,</l>
                     <l>Our offerings muſt be while we live.</l>
                     <l>Two Doves, no Phenix, you muſt be.</l>
                     <l>I muſt ſee that live, comes from me:</l>
                     <l>You as an offering, goe from me,</l>
                     <l>But on your wings, my heart muſt be.</l>
                     <l>My heart now free, from all deſire,</l>
                     <l>But what is kindled by heavens fire.</l>
                     <l>To him, I doe preſent, as free,</l>
                     <l>As ever he did give it me.</l>
                     <l>I on your wings, would ſore aloft,</l>
                     <l>And ſtill live free from humane thought.</l>
                     <l>Accept great God, what I preſent,</l>
                     <l>Thy glory is my Souls intent.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Goe now my Doves, and ſoar aloft,</l>
                     <l>The drooping heart raiſe you full oft,</l>
                     <l>To ſuch a heigth, bear it away,</l>
                     <l>That it may ſee celeſtiall day,</l>
                     <l>And never lett it on earth reſt;</l>
                     <l>But leave it in Heavens glorious breſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Trimph.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SIth thou from thrall haſt ſett me free,</l>
                     <l>I will ſing prayſes unto thee.</l>
                     <l>Thou haſt brought me from Temptation,</l>
                     <l>And fild me with contemplation</l>
                     <l>Of thy heavenly habitation,</l>
                     <l>In which lives a glorious Nation,</l>
                     <l>Which triumphantly doe ſing,</l>
                     <l>Praiſe and glory to their King.</l>
                     <l>No<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> darkneſſe, nor no dolefull night,</l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:169720:7"/>
                     <l>Obſcures their Viſion of delight,</l>
                     <l>No noiſe doth interrupt their voice,</l>
                     <l>They doe inceſſantly rejoyce.</l>
                     <l>Mayſt thou my Soule, now be ſo bold,</l>
                     <l>That glorious place for to behold,</l>
                     <l>And ſay, how that faire Cities bleſt,</l>
                     <l>In which the righteous ſhall have reſt.</l>
                     <l>The wals are rais'd of Gems more bright,</l>
                     <l>Then are the Diamonds here in ſight:</l>
                     <l>The Saphire, Diamond, Ruby fine,</l>
                     <l>Their beauty in each one combine.</l>
                     <l>The other Gems their luſtre bright,</l>
                     <l>With them doe give ſo fine a light;</l>
                     <l>That like the Rainbow it doth ſhow,</l>
                     <l>But far more bright, you'l think I know.</l>
                     <l>Moſt glorious things, are ſaid of thee</l>
                     <l>Thou City, where the mighties bee,</l>
                     <l>The ſtreets, are of the pureſt mold,</l>
                     <l>Exceeding farr, the brighteſt gold;</l>
                     <l>And from Gods glorious Throne doth ſpring</l>
                     <l>A River that ſweet pleaſures bring,</l>
                     <l>Adorn'd with many a goodly tree,</l>
                     <l>Which freſh and flouriſhing ever bee.</l>
                     <l>They doe not onely pleaſe the eye,</l>
                     <l>But heal the wounds, would make us dye,</l>
                     <l>Nor fruitleſſe doe their trees appear,</l>
                     <l>But pleaſant fruit yeeld all the year.</l>
                     <l>I doe not wonder, fruit ſo rife</l>
                     <l>Upon theſe goodly Trees of life.</l>
                     <l>No change, doth in this place appeare,</l>
                     <l>No ſcorching heat, nor cold is here.</l>
                     <l>This heav'n the bright Lamb his wife gives,</l>
                     <l>And ſhe in this place alwayes lives.</l>
                     <l>She is more lovely then the Roſe,</l>
                     <l>Freſh, faire and beauteous, and ſtill goes,</l>
                     <l>In long white Robes, ſo pure and clear,</l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:169720:8"/>
                     <l>Like Orient Pearl ſhe doth appear:</l>
                     <l>And on her head, a Crowne more bright,</l>
                     <l>Then is the Sun, here in our ſight.</l>
                     <l>The pure white Lilly, at her feet,</l>
                     <l>And pleaſant Roſe there ſtrive to meet;</l>
                     <l>For all their beauty and their grace,</l>
                     <l>Is from reflexion of her face.</l>
                     <l>Theſe lovely flowers doe never fade,</l>
                     <l>But for eternity were made.</l>
                     <l>How can this place but pleaſing bee?</l>
                     <l>When here ſuch pleaſures you may ſee!</l>
                     <l>And in this place, you may behold,</l>
                     <l>The ancient Martyrs Crown'd with gold,</l>
                     <l>With Palms of Victory, in their hand,</l>
                     <l>Which were giv'n them at Gods command.</l>
                     <l>By a bright ſtreame like Chriſtall pure,</l>
                     <l>The bleſſed Saints ſit ſafe and ſure.</l>
                     <l>In a faire Grove, pleaſant and ſweet,</l>
                     <l>They with great joy each other meet.</l>
                     <l>And they recount, their troubles paſt,</l>
                     <l>And their tranſcendent joyes at laſt.</l>
                     <l>The Quires of Angels, ſtill do ſing</l>
                     <l>Continuall praiſes, to their King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Like them, let me, be praiſing thee,</l>
                     <l>While here on earth thou'lt have me bee.</l>
                     <l>Here let me drinke, deep of that ſpring</l>
                     <l>That flows from thee, and I ſhall ſing,</l>
                     <l>Sweet praiſes to thy holy name:</l>
                     <l>My tongue and hand, ſhall ſpeake thy fame,</l>
                     <l>I ſtill muſt end my God to thee,</l>
                     <l>All praiſe and glory given bee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>To my Siſter. <hi>S. G.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HEavens bright ſhining ſtar, ſhine in thy face,</l>
                     <l>Thy mortall body, with rare vertues grace.</l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:169720:8"/>
                     <l>I wiſh thoſe beams may ſtill thy ſoul inwrap,</l>
                     <l>That Satan may not thy ſweet ſoul intrap.</l>
                     <l>From his malicious ſnares, I wiſh thee free,</l>
                     <l>That thou mayſt have thy ſoule at liberty.</l>
                     <l>Set not thy heart upon theſe fading pleaſures,</l>
                     <l>Thou art an heire to heavens eternall treaſures.</l>
                     <l>Their vain delights will not abide, but vaniſh</l>
                     <l>From thy pure ſoul, in youth them quickly baniſh,</l>
                     <l>If thou delight in them they'l breed thy paine,</l>
                     <l>But if thou baniſh them, then ſhalt thou gaine</l>
                     <l>To thy high-borne Soul immortal treaſure,</l>
                     <l>Celeſtiall joy, true eternall pleaſure.</l>
                     <l>Then here on earth thy heaven thou ſhalt begin,</l>
                     <l>For pleaſures vaine, intice thee unto ſin.</l>
                     <l>Vaine pleaſure ſoon, Sweet Siſter doe thou fly,</l>
                     <l>That ſin in thee, may fade full ſoon and dye.</l>
                     <l>Fix thou thine eyes on that faire Sun of light,</l>
                     <l>Who aye inwrap thee in his beames moſt bright</l>
                     <l>Dazle and blinde thine eyes, to earthly things,</l>
                     <l>Ope them in Heaven, where his ſweet angels ſings.</l>
                     <l>He bring thy ſoul to that immortall place,</l>
                     <l>Where like the Sun ſhall ſhine thy mortall face.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I know you pleas'd will be, to hear of me,</l>
                     <l>If I am bleſt or happy, you ſhall ſee.</l>
                     <l>My Soul, I therefore now have ſent you dreſt,</l>
                     <l>When ſo ſhee's tyr'd, ſhe cannot but be bleſt.</l>
                     <l>My glory and my Lord have tane from me</l>
                     <l>The garments of ſad mourning, you ſhall ſee:</l>
                     <l>Upon her head a Crowne of joy he'ath plac't,</l>
                     <l>How can ſhe be but happy, when ſo grac't.</l>
                     <l>The bright faire robe of honour ſhee hath on,</l>
                     <l>Which can be giv'n but by himſelfe alone,</l>
                     <l>Seeing he hath dreſt me for his throne of glory,</l>
                     <l>But I muſt ſtay to act another Story.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:169720:9"/>
                  <head>Canticles 2.</head>
                  <p>THe Winter is paſt, the Summer is come, I will now ſolace my ſelfe in the Vineyards of my beloved; for he will guide me here by his Counſell, and at length receive me to his Glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Rapture.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>MOſt people hover here below,</l>
                     <l>Too neer the earth, Ile not doe ſo;</l>
                     <l>But Ile ariſe, and to Heaven goe,</l>
                     <l>I will not tarry here below.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This earthly ſtate's, too meane for mee,</l>
                     <l>Ile flee where the bright Angels bee,</l>
                     <l>That ſtill the face of God doe ſee,</l>
                     <l>With them, my Soul can beſt agree,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Mong them Ile ſet me downe and ſing,</l>
                     <l>The praiſes of our glorious King,</l>
                     <l>By him we have our bleſt being,</l>
                     <l>We with delight his praiſes ſing.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Still in this Rapture let me bide,</l>
                     <l>And from this pleaſing bliſſe nev'r glide,</l>
                     <l>But be like to the Eagle ey'd.</l>
                     <l>I have juſt now methinks deſcride</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The glorious Sun in Heaven ſo bright,</l>
                     <l>On this tranſcendent throne of light;</l>
                     <l>It dazles now my humane ſight;</l>
                     <l>The luſte of it is ſo bright.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:169720:9"/>
                     <l>I would not now with mortals be,</l>
                     <l>To tell them in what bliſſe are we.</l>
                     <l>Let them ariſe, and come to me,</l>
                     <l>If they would know our dignity.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O let me not to earth now goe,</l>
                     <l>How dark and hideous, it doth ſhow,</l>
                     <l>They crawl like Ants methinks below,</l>
                     <l>Among ſuch Creatures I'de not goe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But if to earth thou wilt have me,</l>
                     <l>To doe what thy will doth decree;</l>
                     <l>Let me deſeend more willingly;</l>
                     <l>By me thy will muſt acted bee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But yet before I goe away</l>
                     <l>Grant I beſeech, for what I pray,</l>
                     <l>Or let me here with thee ſtill ſtay,</l>
                     <l>Take no offence at my delay.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh let thy heavenly Sun of light</l>
                     <l>With me ſend down his beams moſt bright,</l>
                     <l>So to my ſoule ſhall be no night,</l>
                     <l>She being inwrapt in Heav'ns bright light.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Flight.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>ELiza</hi> for, aske now not here,</l>
                     <l>She's gone to heaven, to meet her Peer.</l>
                     <l>For ſince her Lord, on earth was dead,</l>
                     <l>What tarry here! ſhe'd not, ſhe ſed.</l>
                     <l>And to the heavens, ſhe took her flight,</l>
                     <l>That ſhe might be ſtill in his ſight,</l>
                     <l>And ſo to us ſhe bid adieu,</l>
                     <l>But prov'd her ſelfe a lover true.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:169720:10"/>
                  <head>The Life.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IF as men ſay, we live not, where we are,</l>
                     <l>But where we love,</l>
                     <l>I live above.</l>
                     <l>For what on earth, or yet in heaven is there</l>
                     <l>Deſir'd can be,</l>
                     <l>'Tis none but thee.</l>
                     <l>Great God, thou onely worth deſiring art,</l>
                     <l>And none but thee, then muſt poſſeſſe my heart.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>My Wiſhes.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I Wiſh no wit to wrong my Brother,</l>
                     <l>I wiſh not wealth to wrong another;</l>
                     <l>I wiſh no beauty to enthrall,</l>
                     <l>I wiſh no worldly wiſh at all.</l>
                     <l>I wiſh from ſin God would me bring,</l>
                     <l>I wiſh for heaven, at my ending.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a paine at heart.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>GOd laid his hand upon my heart,</l>
                     <l>To ſee, if I would from it part:</l>
                     <l>I was content to let it goe,</l>
                     <l>I lik't it beſt to have it ſo;</l>
                     <l>For then no more it ſhould be pain'd,</l>
                     <l>When it with him a place had gain'd,</l>
                     <l>But hee'd hav't here, a few more dayes,</l>
                     <l>An Inſtrument unto his praiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Portion.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHat if the world on me ſhould frown,</l>
                     <l>Thou art my Crown;</l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:169720:10"/>
                     <l>If wealth and beauty part away,</l>
                     <l>Thou art my ſtay.</l>
                     <l>Let others count this world a hell,</l>
                     <l>In it I'me well;</l>
                     <l>No wonder, if I happy be,</l>
                     <l>Sith, I'me in thee;</l>
                     <l>For why? in thee all bliſſe doth dwell,</l>
                     <l>Then here to me can be no hell.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Friday before Eaſter.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHy ſhould I now, lament &amp; moan?</l>
                     <l>The bleſſed ſeed, to day was ſown,</l>
                     <l>Shall never in the earth decay,</l>
                     <l>But riſe in triumph, the third day.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>On Eaſter day.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A Riſe and ſee, why doſt thou ſleep,</l>
                     <l>The bed of earth, could not him keep,</l>
                     <l>The Sun is riſſe, that made the day,</l>
                     <l>In grave, thou needs fear no decay.</l>
                     <l>Thoſe glorious beams hath made the earth,</l>
                     <l>A place to give thee a new birth.</l>
                     <l>From Mothers wombe thou cam'ſt to be</l>
                     <l>A Creature of Mortality;</l>
                     <l>From wombe of earth, thou rais'd ſhalt bee,</l>
                     <l>A creature like the Deity;</l>
                     <l>When thou art pleas'd, that I ſhall dye,</l>
                     <l>I am content in earth to lye:</l>
                     <l>There ſhall I ſafely lye and reſt,</l>
                     <l>Till thou wilt raiſe me with the bleſt.</l>
                     <l>Though I could wiſh, that it might bee</l>
                     <l>As were my childiſh thoughts in mee,</l>
                     <l>That like <hi>Elias</hi> I might riſe,</l>
                     <l>On Cherubs wings, in Chariot wiſe:</l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:169720:11"/>
                     <l>To thy bright heaven, where I might bee,</l>
                     <l>There cloath'd with immortality:</l>
                     <l>Thoſe thoughts were childiſh tis confeſt,</l>
                     <l>In grave<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I muſt be ſor heaven dreſt.</l>
                     <l>The earth a while, my body muſt retaine,</l>
                     <l>Though as a King, my Soul in heaven doth reign.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Pavillion.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>ON thy fair wings, moſt ſacred Dove,</l>
                     <l>Let me be rais'd, with thee on high</l>
                     <l>Unto the heavenly God of Love,</l>
                     <l>Where I ſhal reſt me quietly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No ill ſhall there my Dove affright,</l>
                     <l>I'le bid all feare on earth adieu,</l>
                     <l>For I am now at ſuch a height,</l>
                     <l>As cannot reached be by you.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In this Pavillion I ſhall ſing,</l>
                     <l>Though I may ſee you fly at me,</l>
                     <l>I am aſſur'd by his bright wing,</l>
                     <l>He will not let me wounded bee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Submiſſion.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>MY ſoul to Heaven would haſt &amp; fly,</l>
                     <l>And there make ſuit, that I may die</l>
                     <l>Becauſe from heaven ſhe is detain'd,</l>
                     <l>Lives in a body ſometimes pain'd:</l>
                     <l>And in her glory cannot be,</l>
                     <l>So long, as here ſhe ſtayes in me.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But that thy will ſhee doth reſpect,</l>
                     <l>And looks to what thou haſt elect,</l>
                     <l>And will contented be to ſtay;</l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:169720:11"/>
                     <l>That here thy will, ſhe might obey:</l>
                     <l>She wiſheth rather to pleaſe thee,</l>
                     <l>Then in her glory for to bee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Change.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VAine world, when as I loved thee.</l>
                     <l>Dire ſadneſſe ſtill poſſeſſed me,</l>
                     <l>But ſince I lernt to diſpiſe thee,</l>
                     <l>Sweet joys and gladneſſe filleth me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Choice.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HEavenly treaſure,</l>
                     <l>In ſome meaſure</l>
                     <l>Haſt thou here unto me ſent,</l>
                     <l>Yet I would dye,</l>
                     <l>And to heav'n fly</l>
                     <l>To poſſeſſe a full content.</l>
                     <l>My ſoul's ſweet joy</l>
                     <l>Nought doth annoy:</l>
                     <l>But my body's ſometimes pain'd,</l>
                     <l>I cannot bee</l>
                     <l>From all ill free,</l>
                     <l>Till bright heaven, I have obtain'd</l>
                     <l>Here the ſtory</l>
                     <l>Of thy glory</l>
                     <l>Is that which doth me delight;</l>
                     <l>But ſure more joy,</l>
                     <l>With no annoy</l>
                     <l>Muſt be in thy Palace bright,</l>
                     <l>With ſpeed thy will</l>
                     <l>Let me fulfill,</l>
                     <l>And take me to thy heavenly light.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:169720:12"/>
                  <head>The Reſt.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>FRom Heaven ſtill flows ſuch ſweet Celeſtiall joy,</l>
                     <l>That this earths troubles ſhall not me annoy;</l>
                     <l>For I above them ſhall ſet ſafe and free,</l>
                     <l>And underneath me ſhall them gliding ſee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The morning Star.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>BRight morning ſtar of heavenly light,</l>
                     <l>Riſe to my Soul, and baniſh night,</l>
                     <l>And with thy fair bright beams expell</l>
                     <l>Thoſe clouds that make this world like hell:</l>
                     <l>And with thy ſweet attractive power,</l>
                     <l>Raiſe thou me, to thy bliſſefull bower:</l>
                     <l>Where being rais'd, let me aye reſt,</l>
                     <l>Fixt in the Region of thy breſt;</l>
                     <l>Where like a bright ſtar I ſhall ſhine,</l>
                     <l>I being array'd in rayes of thine.</l>
                     <l>And to the darkeſome world ſhine bright,</l>
                     <l>I living in thy glorious light.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The worlds farewell.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>NOw to the world I bid adieu,</l>
                     <l>I'me haſting better things to view:</l>
                     <l>To Heavens faire Palace ſhining bright,</l>
                     <l>It may be I may fly to night,</l>
                     <l>And'mong bright Angels ſpend my time,</l>
                     <l>To hear and ſee, but what's Divine:</l>
                     <l>And with an Orient light be clad,</l>
                     <l>And live like to the Angels glad;</l>
                     <l>For what makes me ſo joyfull here,</l>
                     <l>Cauſe in thy robes, I ſhall appear.</l>
                     <l>Lye thou my body in theeath,</l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:169720:12"/>
                     <l>Till thou ſhalt gain a better birth.</l>
                     <l>From earth thou cam'ſt ſpotted with ſin,</l>
                     <l>And thither ſo return'ſt agen.</l>
                     <l>When thou art purified then <hi>I</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shall take thee and thou ſhalt not dye:</l>
                     <l>And when the Trumpet thou doſt hear,</l>
                     <l>Thou in thy glory ſhalt appear.</l>
                     <l>A King doth come to bring that lott,</l>
                     <l>Which he himſelfe for thee hath got,</l>
                     <l>A Kingdom 'tis, of joy and glory,</l>
                     <l>And now, I end my earthly ſtory.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Swans.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>FAire Swans, you now beyond me go,</l>
                     <l>In pleaſant Robes, like pure white ſnow,</l>
                     <l>But I ere long ſhall be more bright,</l>
                     <l>In faire eternall robes of light.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Your fair robes fall and fade away,</l>
                     <l>But my bright robes, ſhall nev'r decay.</l>
                     <l>You ſing they ſay, before you dye,</l>
                     <l>But when I'me dead, then ſing ſhall I.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>To a friend at Court.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>REtired here content I live,</l>
                     <l>My own thoughts to me pleaſure give.</l>
                     <l>While thine owne actions anger thee,</l>
                     <l>Sweet quiet thoughts contenteth me.</l>
                     <l>This bleſſing ſweet retiredneſſe brings,</l>
                     <l>We envy none, but pity Kings.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:169720:13"/>
                  <head>Chriſts Kingdome.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WIth you bleſt Angels, I muſt ſing,</l>
                     <l>That brought the news of heav'ns great King</l>
                     <l>That from bright Heaven awhile did part,</l>
                     <l>To raiſe his Kingdome with my heart.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Before he came there was great ſtrife,</l>
                     <l>To lead me to a helliſh life:</l>
                     <l>But like an humble Babe cam'ſt thou,</l>
                     <l>Yet made thoſe mighty powers to bow.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou didſt regain me for thy right,</l>
                     <l>For I at firſt ſprang from thy light,</l>
                     <l>Satan aſide a while drew me,</l>
                     <l>But could not keep me Lord from thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When thou haſt caſt off that foule fin,</l>
                     <l>Thy Kingdome in me didſt begin,</l>
                     <l>And here thou wilt ſtill reign in me,</l>
                     <l>Till I ſhallcome and reigne with thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A thy approach, black ſhades did vaniſh,</l>
                     <l>And from my heart thou fearc didſt baniſh,</l>
                     <l>And in their room did light appear,</l>
                     <l>And joy inſtead of dreadly feare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sweet joy and peace, thou didſt bring me,</l>
                     <l>How can I chuſe but ſing to thee:</l>
                     <l>To my great God all glory be,</l>
                     <l>Thou plac'ſt his Kingdome here in me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:169720:13"/>
                  <head>Vaine thoughts baniſht.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A Dieu vain thoughtt, Adieu, Adieu,</l>
                     <l>My Soule no more delights in you,</l>
                     <l>You'r no companion for my ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>I muſt a heaven of bliſſe inherit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Your darkneſſe dims my ſouls cleare fight,</l>
                     <l>And you debar me of heavens light:</l>
                     <l>When free from you I heaven can view;</l>
                     <l>Vain thoughts, I now will baniſh you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>My intention.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>GO vaine invention, get you hence,</l>
                     <l>With me make not your reſidence,</l>
                     <l>Court not my Muſe with fine invention,</l>
                     <l>To praiſe my God tis my intention,</l>
                     <l>Lord let no line be writ by me,</l>
                     <l>That excludes, or includes not thee,</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Earths honour ſlighted.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>OF Earthly honour tell not me;</l>
                     <l>The vanity of it I ſee:</l>
                     <l>Tis like a flower that ſoon doth riſe,</l>
                     <l>If ruffly ſtruck it falls and dies.</l>
                     <l>But that bright honour which I priſe,</l>
                     <l>Sweetly ſprings up and never dies;</l>
                     <l>And's like the Sun whoſe pleaſing ray,</l>
                     <l>Doth baniſh night, and bring the day:</l>
                     <l>His pleaſant ſweet attractive light,</l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:169720:14"/>
                     <l>Raiſeth me to a heavenly hight.</l>
                     <l>With this fair honour being dreſt,</l>
                     <l>I'me free from fear, and live in reſt.</l>
                     <l>'Tis heavenly honour I eſteem,</l>
                     <l>All earthly honour vain I deem:</l>
                     <l>The one is made to fall and dye,</l>
                     <l>I love what bides eternally.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Luke 20. 36.</hi> In that world they ſhall be equall to the Angels.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HEre like the Angels let me be,</l>
                     <l>And as thoſe bleſſed ſpirits free:</l>
                     <l>From vaine engagements let me bide,</l>
                     <l>And as they with thee ſtill reſide.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Like them I'me made, by my new birth,</l>
                     <l>But I'me ſtill wrapt in robes of earth.</l>
                     <l>Through a darke mantle I thee ſee,</l>
                     <l>But oh that I unwrapt may be.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This bleſſing now on earth me give,</l>
                     <l>That like thine Angels I might live.</l>
                     <l>So ſhall my ſoul ſuch ſweet joys find,</l>
                     <l>That earthly things I ſhall not minde.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the morning riſe.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>NOw welcome ſweet and pleaſant Morn,</l>
                     <l>Doe you not thinke, that I you ſcorn:</l>
                     <l>Cauſe with a more Orientall light,</l>
                     <l>Imbelliſht is my bleſt ſpirit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>With thanks I ſtill you entertaine.</l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:169720:14"/>
                     <l>For by your light, my eye-fight gain:</l>
                     <l>But you are darkneſſe, to that light,</l>
                     <l>That is diſcride, by my ſouls ſights.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon hearing the Birds ſing.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SWeet Birds with you Ile ſet and ſing,</l>
                     <l>Due praiſes to our heavenly King.</l>
                     <l>Like you me thinks, I am as free,</l>
                     <l>So made great divine Prince by thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>My Robes.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I Will not now to thee Lord come</l>
                     <l>As I from <hi>Adam</hi> came,</l>
                     <l>But I will come as in thy Son,</l>
                     <l>His Robys ſhall hide my ſhame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He is my Spouſe, and my lov'd Lord,</l>
                     <l>In him thou loveſt me,</l>
                     <l>I to thy will would ſtill accord,</l>
                     <l>And with him ſtill agree.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In his bright Robes, I will preſent</l>
                     <l>My ſelfe to thee and ſay,</l>
                     <l>To doe thy will is my intent;</l>
                     <l>In him I thee obey.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou canſt not now, Lord me reject,</l>
                     <l>Thou muſt me perfect ſee:</l>
                     <l>His beauty both on me reflect,</l>
                     <l>I'me beautifull to thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:169720:15"/>
                  <head>The Dart.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SHoot from above</l>
                     <l>Thou God of Love,</l>
                     <l>And with heav'ns dart</l>
                     <l>Wound my bleſt heart.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Deſcend ſweet life,</l>
                     <l>And end this ſtrife:</l>
                     <l>Earth would me ſtay,</l>
                     <l>But I'le away.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I'le dye for love</l>
                     <l>Of thee above,</l>
                     <l>Then ſhould I bee</l>
                     <l>Made one with thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And let be ſed</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Eliza</hi>'s dead,</l>
                     <l>And of love dy'd,</l>
                     <l>That love defi'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>By a bright beam, ſhot from above,</l>
                     <l>She did aſcend to her great Love,</l>
                     <l>And was content of love to dye,</l>
                     <l>Shot with a dart of Heavens bright eye.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Of Poetry.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>POets they ſay are always poor,</l>
                     <l>But tis not they are at thy door.</l>
                     <l>They cannot chuſe but wealthy be,</l>
                     <l>For why? Rich poems flow from thee.</l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:169720:15"/>
                     <l>'Tis they that clime the hill, is none of thine,</l>
                     <l>But goe for aid unto the Muſes Nine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No wonder though ſuch fools are poor,</l>
                     <l>That goe for Alms to a wrong door.</l>
                     <l>They ſeek to them to get their wealth,</l>
                     <l>Who have too little for their ſelfe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>To the King. writ, 1644.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>TO thee, Great Monarch of this Iſle</l>
                     <l>I ſend my Babes, pray make them ſmile;</l>
                     <l>For yet methinks tis in thy power,</l>
                     <l>To make them ſmile, or let them lower.</l>
                     <l>They'r children to that Prince of might,</l>
                     <l>Who is the Prince of peace behight.</l>
                     <l>Do not with war my Babes affright,</l>
                     <l>In ſmiling peace is their delight,</l>
                     <l>My Prince by yeelding won the field,</l>
                     <l>Be not too rigid, dear King yeeld:</l>
                     <l>Examples that are great and high.</l>
                     <l>I hope you'l follow, fix your eye</l>
                     <l>On my great prince, that is your King,</l>
                     <l>He left a Heaven, you peace to bring.</l>
                     <l>A Kingdome I'de not have you leave,</l>
                     <l>But rather three reform'd receive.</l>
                     <l>All bliſſe and peace I wiſh to you,</l>
                     <l>Let us in peace, your preſence view.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>To the Queen of Bohemiah.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>LOng ſince, it was by me defir'd,</l>
                     <l>To ſee that Queen ſo much admir'd;</l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:169720:16"/>
                     <l>But well I knew, t'was not for mee,</l>
                     <l>Great Princeſſes to goe to fee.</l>
                     <l>But thraldomes key, did let me out,</l>
                     <l>And trouble brought my wiſh about,</l>
                     <l>By thraldome then I freedome gain'd,</l>
                     <l>By trouble my deſire obtain'd.</l>
                     <l>I then did ſee her ſo admir'd,</l>
                     <l>And thy rich graces Lord inſpir'd.</l>
                     <l>A minde ſo great and bravely beare,</l>
                     <l>What in the moſt breeds care and feare.</l>
                     <l>A ſpirit high ſo humble bee,</l>
                     <l>To deigne her ſweet regards to me.</l>
                     <l>Her I admire, and for her pray</l>
                     <l>On earth ſhe may live many a day:</l>
                     <l>And when this earth ſhe ſhall forſake,</l>
                     <l>That into heaven, thou wouldſt her take,</l>
                     <l>Where ou a Throne ſhe may be Crown'd,</l>
                     <l>And with bright Angels compaſt round.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Lover.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>COme let us now to each diſcover,</l>
                     <l>Who is our friend, and who our Lover,</l>
                     <l>What? art thou now aſham'd of thine,</l>
                     <l>I tell thee true, Ime not of mine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And you will ſay when you him ſee,</l>
                     <l>That none but he, defir'd can bee,</l>
                     <l>He is the onely pleaſing wight,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe preſence can content my ſight.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For He's the pureſt red and white,</l>
                     <l>In whom my ſoule takes her delight:</l>
                     <l>He to the flowrs heir beauty gives,</l>
                     <l>In him the Roſe and Lilly lives,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:169720:16"/>
                     <l>His pleaſant haire with feemly grace,</l>
                     <l>Hangs by his faire ſweet lovely face,</l>
                     <l>And from his pleaſing eyes do dart</l>
                     <l>Their arrows which do pierce my heart.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Theſe beauties all are richly grac'ſt,</l>
                     <l>For on his head, a crown is plac'ſt,</l>
                     <l>Of glory, which doth ſhine ſo bright,</l>
                     <l>As mortall eye can ſee this light,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This lovely Lord's, the Prince of Peace,</l>
                     <l>In him, my joyes will ſtill increaſe;</l>
                     <l>For he's the true, and conſtant friend,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe love begun, will never end.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>From Heaven he came with me to dwell,</l>
                     <l>And ſav'd my ſoul from direfull hell,</l>
                     <l>'Tis he alone my heart doth gaine,</l>
                     <l>That keeps me from eternall pain.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>While here I live, here he will bee;</l>
                     <l>Death cannot ſeparate him from me:</l>
                     <l>And when I dye, he will me place,</l>
                     <l>Where I ſhall ever ſee his face.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Into his glory, hee'l take mee,</l>
                     <l>This doe I know, this ſhall you ſee</l>
                     <l>And now you know my loved friend,</l>
                     <l>My loves begun, it will not end.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The renowned King.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>LAdies! if beauty you deſire,</l>
                     <l>Or to high fortunes doe aſpire,</l>
                     <l>Come now with me I have deſcride,</l>
                     <l>A Prince, that to all, can you guide.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:169720:17"/>
                     <l>He is a King of great renown,</l>
                     <l>And on your head can place a Crowne.</l>
                     <l>And with immortall beauty bleſſe,</l>
                     <l>Can you wiſh more? yet wiſh no leſſe</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If you deſire this Prince to ſee,</l>
                     <l>Then leave the world and goe with me,</l>
                     <l>To true Eliſian fields, i'le guide</l>
                     <l>You, where I this great Prince eſpi'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The holy leaves of Sacred writ</l>
                     <l>Are thoſe Eliſians, there let's gett,</l>
                     <l>Where with joy we ſhall him finde,</l>
                     <l>This glorious Prince will pleaſe your mind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He's like the Roſe in Sharon fields,</l>
                     <l>Pleaſant to ſight, and ſweetneſſe yeelds,</l>
                     <l>With ſweet and faire, from his bright face,</l>
                     <l>The Lilly and the Roſe gets grace,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>With ſerious thoughts now him behold</l>
                     <l>If you him love you may be bold,</l>
                     <l>And in his preſence ever bee,</l>
                     <l>His beauty will reflect on thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If thou get beauty from his face,</l>
                     <l>He will you take from your mean place,</l>
                     <l>And on his Throne he will ſet thee,</l>
                     <l>Where with his Crown thou crown'd ſhalt bee,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That beauty ſtill with thee will ſtay,</l>
                     <l>Time will not carry it away.</l>
                     <l>That Crowne ſhall no man take from thee,</l>
                     <l>But thou ſhalt wear't eternally.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:169720:17"/>
                  <head>To my Siſter, <hi>S. S.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SWeet Siſter, Let us in Heaven greet,</l>
                     <l>Since here on earth we cannot meet</l>
                     <l>Hard by that ſtream of Chriſtall pure,</l>
                     <l>To meet thee there I will be ſure.</l>
                     <l>That ſtreame which from this Throne doth riſe;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe waters pure cure our ill eyes:</l>
                     <l>Then let us ſit us downe and reſt,</l>
                     <l>No enemies ſhall us there moleſt.</l>
                     <l>Lets leave our bodies here as dead,</l>
                     <l>When thus our Soules to heaven are fled:</l>
                     <l>Where we poſſeſſe a raviſht joy,</l>
                     <l>When as the world lies in annoy.</l>
                     <l>Let's take thoſe waters now and drink,</l>
                     <l>'Twill make us then no more to think</l>
                     <l>Of theſe baſe follies here below,</l>
                     <l>Dear Siſter, let us both doe ſo.</l>
                     <l>Then let us ſet us down and tell</l>
                     <l>By whom we were redeem'd from hell,</l>
                     <l>T'was he that ſits on you bright Throne,</l>
                     <l>Wrought our redemption all alone.</l>
                     <l>Who would not now their ſoules prize high,</l>
                     <l>For whom ſo great a Prince did die.</l>
                     <l>Come let us up thoſe ſtreams and ſee,</l>
                     <l>Where thoſe bright glories ſitting bee.</l>
                     <l>There Three in One conjoyn'd we ſee,</l>
                     <l>And yet each Perſon differing be.</l>
                     <l>There ſets our powerfull God alone,</l>
                     <l>Upon his glorious heavenly Throne,</l>
                     <l>At his right hand ſits his dear Son,</l>
                     <l>Oh! Who would think he'd let him come</l>
                     <l>From that bright Throne to ſuffer here.</l>
                     <l>And for our ſakes vile to appear.</l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:169720:18"/>
                     <l>Ten thouſand, thouſand Angels bee</l>
                     <l>Tending about his Throne you ſee:</l>
                     <l>They ſing the praiſes of that King,</l>
                     <l>Oh hear, how rare, and ſweet they ſing!</l>
                     <l>My ſenſes now are raviſht quite,</l>
                     <l>My Soule is fill'd with ſuch delight,</l>
                     <l>That if I now my choice might have,</l>
                     <l>They ſhould my body lay in grave,</l>
                     <l>And ſay, That I did chuſe to dye,</l>
                     <l>And let my body on earth lye,</l>
                     <l>Till it moſt glorious ſhould bee,</l>
                     <l>Like to Thoſe Angels that we ſee.</l>
                     <l>The holy Spirit there doth bide,</l>
                     <l>For in the Son they all reſide.</l>
                     <l>No bodily preſence doth appear,</l>
                     <l>But of that God that ſufferd here.</l>
                     <l>Theſe glories cannot limned bee</l>
                     <l>By my frail pencell, well I ſee.</l>
                     <l>Now let us down thoſe banks, like green.</l>
                     <l>Rich Velvet, whereupon are ſeen</l>
                     <l>Bright orient Pearl, and Rubies fair,</l>
                     <l>Strow'd on the velvet here and there,</l>
                     <l>Bright Diamonds ſcattered there doe lye,</l>
                     <l>Look! there ſprings up the violet by:</l>
                     <l>As if a pride that ſweet flower took,</l>
                     <l>Her face in that bright Gem to look,</l>
                     <l>The pure white Violet doth delight,</l>
                     <l>To hang upon that Ruby bright,</l>
                     <l>The ſweet Carnation Pink that growes</l>
                     <l>By that rich Pearl, howe fine it ſhow's.</l>
                     <l>Now let us on theſe ſweet bancks reſt,</l>
                     <l>Methinks we are divinely bleſt.</l>
                     <l>Look by thoſe chriſtall ſtremas, there grows</l>
                     <l>The Lilly fair, and lovely Roſe.</l>
                     <l>How in the waters they doe ſhow,</l>
                     <l>Bright er then they do where they grow.</l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:169720:18"/>
                     <l>A Luſtre fine thoſe waters give</l>
                     <l>Unto thoſe plants that by them live.</l>
                     <l>Come let us now goe walk and ſee,</l>
                     <l>Like whom we ſhall hereafter be,</l>
                     <l>See there <hi>Elias</hi> doth appear</l>
                     <l>Like to the Angels that are here,</l>
                     <l>I did forget; we ſhall in light,</l>
                     <l>Be like his glorious body bright,</l>
                     <l>But hark! Methinks I hear one ſay,</l>
                     <l>Thou muſt from Heaven to Earth away:</l>
                     <l>You muſt your children goe and teach,</l>
                     <l>How they this bleſſed place may reach,</l>
                     <l>Twill be a pleaſant ſight to ſee</l>
                     <l>Their faces like thoſe Angels bee,</l>
                     <l>The which ere while, we did behold,</l>
                     <l>In Robes more bright then is the gold;</l>
                     <l>The which on earth we think ſo fine,</l>
                     <l>When we in thoſe baſe mettals ſhine,</l>
                     <l>But yet before you goe away,</l>
                     <l>Here me a little what I ſay:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If croſſe you find things goe below,</l>
                     <l>On earth a while it muſt be ſo,</l>
                     <l>Let it not trouble your bleſt mind,</l>
                     <l>In Heaven you ſhall no croſſneſs find,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If any aske you how I fare,</l>
                     <l>Then tell them ſure I'me free from care;</l>
                     <l>For I'me in heaven, you left me there.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Viſion.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHy from celeſtiall bliſs, did you</l>
                     <l>Draw me? theſe meaner things to view,</l>
                     <l>Through thoſe faire gates of pearl, get I</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:169720:19"/>
                     <l>And that moſt pleaſant wall paſt by,</l>
                     <l>Up that pure river ſtrait I went,</l>
                     <l>That from the throne takes his aſcent,</l>
                     <l>Then to the glorious throne I got,</l>
                     <l>Where I did ſee, O God, what not:</l>
                     <l>For whatſoever doth excell,</l>
                     <l>In thee, doth in perfection dwell.</l>
                     <l>That glorious Luſtre and bright ray</l>
                     <l>Made me forget my mortallday.</l>
                     <l>Me thought that fine Orientall light,</l>
                     <l>Made me like it appear as bright.</l>
                     <l>From theſe ſweet joyes why draw you me</l>
                     <l>My ſelf in meaner Robes to ſee?</l>
                     <l>For ſince I us'd to heaven to go,</l>
                     <l>All things on earth do ſordid ſhow.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Heart.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>TWo hearts in one breaſt can there not remain,</l>
                     <l>The one heart puts the other heart to pain.</l>
                     <l>My heart I will ſtill keep, take thou thine own,</l>
                     <l>My heart is happy when diſturb'd by none.</l>
                     <l>Without a heart I know you cannot live,</l>
                     <l>Therefore your own I freely to you give.</l>
                     <l>Mine is in Heaven, and will admit no change,</l>
                     <l>To leave my reſt in heaven, on earth to range.</l>
                     <l>I'de have it written in my happy ſtory,</l>
                     <l>None had my heart but heav'ns great prince of glory</l>
                     <l>My youths affection, to him I did ſend,</l>
                     <l>None can have any but what he will lend.</l>
                     <l>From mortall thraldome deare Prince keep thou me</l>
                     <l>So though on earth, I as in heaven ſhall bee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:169720:19"/>
                  <head>The Bride.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SIth you me ask, Why borne was I?</l>
                     <l>I'le tell you; twas to heaven to fly,</l>
                     <l>Not here to live a ſlaviſh life,</l>
                     <l>By being to the world a wife.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When I was born, I was ſet free,</l>
                     <l>From mortals thraldom here to bee;</l>
                     <l>For that great Prince prepar'd a bride,</l>
                     <l>That for my love on earth here dy'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>May not I then earths thraldom ſcorn,</l>
                     <l>Sith for heavens Prince I here was born?</l>
                     <l>If match't in heaven I weare a Crown,</l>
                     <l>But earthly thra'dome puls me downe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>On the day dedicated to the God of Heaven.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>LOrd, if this day belongs to thee,</l>
                     <l>No part of it pertains to mee.</l>
                     <l>Then ſith this Day, is wholly thine.</l>
                     <l>Let thoughts and actions be divine.</l>
                     <l>Let my ſoule, be divinely clad,</l>
                     <l>And let me be like Angels glad.</l>
                     <l>With Angels food, this day feed mee,</l>
                     <l>And let heav'ns Nectar my drink bee.</l>
                     <l>And to compleat my hearts deſire</l>
                     <l>Send downe a beam of heav'ns bright fire.</l>
                     <l>By it let me that pure path ſee,</l>
                     <l>That leads to glorious bliſs and thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:169720:20"/>
                  <head>The Defiance.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>COme now tumultuous flouds and ſhow,</l>
                     <l>Your ſpite by tumults, you ſhall know,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Eliza's</hi> plac'ſt above your reach</l>
                     <l>Upon her ſoul you make no breach,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Unto the world, you do let ſee</l>
                     <l>You'd have her looſe, but gain ſhall ſhee.</l>
                     <l>What you can get ſhe doth not mind,</l>
                     <l>Her treaſure lies not in your wind.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>When my Brother was ſick.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IF that my Brother thou wilt take from me,</l>
                     <l>Lord with thy will make me contented be.</l>
                     <l>But if it be, thy bleſſed will my Lord,</l>
                     <l>To my requeſt to bend and to accord.</l>
                     <l>And if no harm, to him, that it might bee</l>
                     <l>In this requeſt, then gracious God hear me,</l>
                     <l>And grant, that well and long, he here may live,</l>
                     <l>And honor thee, and glory to thee give.</l>
                     <l>And be an inſtrument here of thy praiſe,</l>
                     <l>And in thy ſervice, ſpend and end his daies.</l>
                     <l>But if in his young years, my Lord thou pleaſe</l>
                     <l>From paine and grief to take him unto eaſe.</l>
                     <l>And if thou fitter doſt my Brother ſee,</l>
                     <l>With thee to raign in glory, then to be,</l>
                     <l>Here ſubject to a world of ſlaviſh fears;</l>
                     <l>For in this mortall world we muſt have cares.</l>
                     <l>Onely in heaven we ſhall ſweet freedom gain,</l>
                     <l>In heaven, there is no fear, no care, nor pain.</l>
                     <l>Then to thy holy will, my gracious Lord,</l>
                     <l>Make me thy ſervant ever to accord.</l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:169720:20"/>
                     <l>And if to Heaven thou wilt my Brother take,</l>
                     <l>I pray thee teach my ſoul for to forſake</l>
                     <l>Vain earthly thoughts, and flee from earth to thee,</l>
                     <l>So with my Brothers ſoul my ſoul ſhall bee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My wiſhes are, thoſe beams may raviſh thee,</l>
                     <l>That wrapt me now in ſweet felicity.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Guard.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>YOu bleſſed Angels, that ſtill live,</l>
                     <l>And tendance on us mortals give,</l>
                     <l>From my moſt dear Lord you are ſent,</l>
                     <l>To tend on me, for the intent,</l>
                     <l>From harm and danger me to keep.</l>
                     <l>You are my guard while I do ſleep,</l>
                     <l>I do not grudge for to confeſſe,</l>
                     <l>Nay my poor ſoul can ſay no leſſe;</l>
                     <l>I am unworthy of that favour,</l>
                     <l>Granted to me from my Father,</l>
                     <l>That you on me, ſhould tendance give,</l>
                     <l>Yee which in glory ſtill do live.</l>
                     <l>I have offended him each hour,</l>
                     <l>And done the ill lay in my power.</l>
                     <l>Then you, that ſtill obedient be,</l>
                     <l>Oh! why ſhould you attend on me.</l>
                     <l>This is a myſtery full deep;</l>
                     <l>You being righteous, ſinners keep.</l>
                     <l>My God I pray thee make me know,</l>
                     <l>Why thoſe bleſt Angels ſhould do ſo?</l>
                     <l>For ſhould I my deſerts conſider,</l>
                     <l>My judgement thus I muſt deliver,</l>
                     <l>Into the pit, and dungeon deep</l>
                     <l>Where Satan is adjudg'd to keep:</l>
                     <l>Where fire and brimſtone raging be</l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:169720:21"/>
                     <l>Where pain abides perpetually,</l>
                     <l>Into this place of miſery,</l>
                     <l>There ſhould I goe, when that I dye.</l>
                     <l>Go leave thy thoughts, thy own thoughts leave,</l>
                     <l>And from thy God, anſwer receive.</l>
                     <l>From that fierce place of miſery,</l>
                     <l>Thee for to ſave, the Lord did die.</l>
                     <l>And though no ſin he did commit,</l>
                     <l>He of his goodneſſe thought it fit</l>
                     <l>To take thy ſins, and quit them all,</l>
                     <l>And bid thee then no more to fall.</l>
                     <l>And tells thee, thou needs not to fear:</l>
                     <l>For why of thee he takes the care.</l>
                     <l>And that on earth while thou doſt live,</l>
                     <l>For tendance on thee he will give.</l>
                     <l>His Angels charge, thee to protect,</l>
                     <l>And be the guard of his Elect;</l>
                     <l>His mercy is the onely reaſon</l>
                     <l>We are ſecur'd from Satans Treaſon.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Felicity.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I Am my Gods, and he doth let me ſee</l>
                     <l>In hima true and ſweet felicity.</l>
                     <l>Thoſe ſprings of joy, that riſe ſtill freſh in me,</l>
                     <l>Proceed my dear ſweet heavenly Prince from thee</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>On ſudden Death.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IF thou in haſt ſhalt ſend for me</l>
                     <l>Great God to live in Heaven with thee,</l>
                     <l>Though to ſome minds it ſodain be,</l>
                     <l>It is not ſodain unto me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:169720:21"/>
                  <head>Heaven.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>LOrd thou doſt bring a heaven with thee,</l>
                     <l>Then where I am a heaven muſt be,</l>
                     <l>For thou art ever Lord with mee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Giver engaged to the Receiver.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THou ſaiſt thou art ingag'd to me</l>
                     <l>For what I give, when I'm to thee:</l>
                     <l>Thou doſt accept a gift that's poor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>For it I have ten thouſand more.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Sun Beames.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THy bleſſings, like the Sunbeams bee</l>
                     <l>Reaching from heaven to earth on me.</l>
                     <l>Like a rich Canopy they ſhow,</l>
                     <l>Spreading from Heaven, doth round me flow.</l>
                     <l>'Tis not abundance rich makes me,</l>
                     <l>But a ſufficiency from thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>To my Brother.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>ELiza ſaies when as ſhe dies,</l>
                     <l>Shee'l baniſh tears from all your eyes,</l>
                     <l>Unleſſe for envy you will weep,</l>
                     <l>That you could not her bleſt ſoul keep</l>
                     <l>From her eternall bliſſe and joy,</l>
                     <l>Tolive with yours in earths annoy.</l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:169720:22"/>
                     <l>When you have brought me to my grave,</l>
                     <l>Then tell the world, tis what I'de have,</l>
                     <l>Yee need not ſay you left me dead,</l>
                     <l>But ſay, I am laid in my bed.</l>
                     <l>Where I ſhall ſafely lye and ſleep,</l>
                     <l>For heavens great Emperor doth me keep.</l>
                     <l>'Mong Kings and Princes that attend.</l>
                     <l>Till to our glory we aſcend.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>What I Love.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>GIve me a Soule, give me a Spirit,</l>
                     <l>That flyes from earth, heaven to inherit.</l>
                     <l>But thoſe that grovell here below,</l>
                     <l>What! I love them? I'le not do ſo.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The onely bound.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>MY boundleſſe ſpirits, bounded be in thee,</l>
                     <l>For bounded by no other can they be.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Chriſtians happineſſe.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>GOds high Spirit ſhall thee direct,</l>
                     <l>His Angels ſhall thee ſtill protect.</l>
                     <l>They ſhal thee guard, while thou doſt ſleep,</l>
                     <l>They from all evill ſhall thee keep.</l>
                     <l>So thou no evill needs to fear,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe of thee God takes the care.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:169720:22"/>
                  <head>The Retribution.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IF thou art pleas'd to have my heart,</l>
                     <l>Accept it Lord from me,</l>
                     <l>Sith thou doſt chuſe it for thy part,</l>
                     <l>I give it none but thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Mine eyes to thee I doe preſent,</l>
                     <l>Accept them now of me;</l>
                     <l>For thou unto me haſt them lent,</l>
                     <l>They doe belong to thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thus heart and eyes, and all are thine,</l>
                     <l>That doe belong to me.</l>
                     <l>Before I knew that they were mine,</l>
                     <l>They were all made by thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Gods Commands eaſie.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>MY Lord! how eaſie is thy will</l>
                     <l>Do, as I would be done unto.</l>
                     <l>Thy holy Law I then fulfill,</l>
                     <l>And give the Lord his praiſes due.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why ſhould I to another doe,</l>
                     <l>What I would not have done to me,</l>
                     <l>All praiſes to thee Lord, is due,</l>
                     <l>For all we have proceeds from thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Praiſe.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>GLory to my gracious Lord,</l>
                     <l>Who to my wiſhes doth accord,</l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:169720:23"/>
                     <l>While here I live, I muſt thee praiſe,</l>
                     <l>For as in Heaven I ſpend my dayes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For nought doth here my ſoul annoy,</l>
                     <l>But I poſſeſſe a Heaven of Joy.</l>
                     <l>And when from this bliſſe, thou'le take me,</l>
                     <l>In glorious Heaven my ſoul ſhall be.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Companion.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHo doth an heavenly Muſe injoy,</l>
                     <l>Regards not this vain worlds annoy.</l>
                     <l>Nor can they ever be alone,</l>
                     <l>Heavens Muſe is there Companion.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the loſſe of my Brother.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHen loſſe of ought would thee torment,</l>
                     <l>Cry; 'tis thy will, Lord I'me content.</l>
                     <l>My love muſt not divided be,</l>
                     <l>'Twixt Earth and Heaven, thou'lt have me ſee.</l>
                     <l>My brother from me thou haſt tane,</l>
                     <l>But yet content I muſt remaine.</l>
                     <l>A Brother and a friend was he,</l>
                     <l>But much more thou wilt be to me.</l>
                     <l>When thoughts of abſence moves a tear,</l>
                     <l>Thy will is, that I ſhould forbear,</l>
                     <l>He went not but by thy decree,</l>
                     <l>And I muſt not diſpleaſed be.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>On the Sun.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>AT height of noon, it cannot be,</l>
                     <l>That I can fix mine eyes on thee,</l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:169720:23"/>
                     <l>But when at ſetting; I am bold,</l>
                     <l>With ſetled eyes thee too behold,</l>
                     <l>Converter of Atheiſtick thought,</l>
                     <l>Thou wert to me, when as I ſought</l>
                     <l>A remedy againſt that ſin,</l>
                     <l>Which I too deep was falling in.</l>
                     <l>Some one above thee muſt make thee,</l>
                     <l>Thou govern'd by a God muſt be.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Being told, ſhe was proud.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>MY body, it muſt ſurely dye,</l>
                     <l>Off to be proud then what have I.</l>
                     <l>Yet proud, if they will have me be,</l>
                     <l>My high-borne ſoule, it is of thee.</l>
                     <l>But Lord, my Soul, is none of mine,</l>
                     <l>Shall I be proud, of what is thine?</l>
                     <l>As being thine, from pride I'me free,</l>
                     <l>It is enough I'me freed by thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>My pleaſing Life.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SWeet quiet, ſweet obſcurity,</l>
                     <l>Here in this life, beſt pleaſeth me,</l>
                     <l>Till from earth's thrall I ſhall be free</l>
                     <l>To live in glorious bliſſe with thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When from earths tumults I am free</l>
                     <l>To contemplate great God on thee</l>
                     <l>A heaven of bliſſe in thee I ſee</l>
                     <l>How can this life, but pleaſing be.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nothing of thee merit I can<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>But yet when free from thrall of man,</l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:169720:24"/>
                     <l>I can thee ſerve with heart more free<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then from that thraldome ſtill keep me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>To a Lady unfaithfull.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe Prince of heaven being in love with you</l>
                     <l>Did to his glorious Kingdom, bid Adieu.</l>
                     <l>The heaven, he was awhile content to leave</l>
                     <l>To ſee, if you would his chaſt love receive.</l>
                     <l>You did belong to him, when he you ſent</l>
                     <l>Into the world; but you from him ſoon went,</l>
                     <l>And his chaſt love, ſo pleaſing and ſo ſweet,</l>
                     <l>You left your wanton Paramour to meet,</l>
                     <l>With his unlawfull love you pleas'd your ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>Fye Madam, leave him, he is but an Elf.</l>
                     <l>See what your dear ſweet Prince hath done for you,</l>
                     <l>'Tis very ſtrange, but yet tis vety true.</l>
                     <l>When he did ſee you wantonize with them</l>
                     <l>Who were profeſſed enemies to him:</l>
                     <l>He then with his fierce enemy did fight,</l>
                     <l>To reingain you as his ancient right.</l>
                     <l>He loſt his royal bloud to purchaſe you,</l>
                     <l>How can you then but to this Prince prove true.</l>
                     <l>Can you a Coward love, and ſtain your name</l>
                     <l>By being falſe unto this Prince of fame?</l>
                     <l>Your want onlovers actions hate the light<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>And you'r aſham'd to act them in our ſight.</l>
                     <l>Then here Ile tell you, if you know not it,</l>
                     <l>All your actions, and vain thoughts unfit,</l>
                     <l>Your true and lawfull Lord doth ſtraight eſpie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>He ſees the wanton glances of your eye.</l>
                     <l>Think with your ſelfe, and then you will refraine,</l>
                     <l>You both your ſelf, and your great Lord defame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>I wonder how you can this vain world love,</l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:169720:24"/>
                     <l>As if you did forget your heaven above,</l>
                     <l>And in your ill unlawfull actions live.</l>
                     <l>Your God doth freely all things to you give:</l>
                     <l>Prove you but conſtant to his love and true,</l>
                     <l>All things are lawfull to be us'd by you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Curſe.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IF thou detainſt my right from me,</l>
                     <l>I never will wiſh worſe to thee.</l>
                     <l>Thou ill enough haſt in thy ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>My right to thee will prove an Elf.</l>
                     <l>My Angels will be good to mee,</l>
                     <l>But Devils they will prove to thee.</l>
                     <l>A Metamorphis ſtrange I ſee,</l>
                     <l>Angels with me, Devils with thee;</l>
                     <l>Thus while I wiſh no ill to thee,</l>
                     <l>With what I have God will bleſſe me.</l>
                     <l>And will with what thou doſt detain</l>
                     <l>Put thee to a moſt helliſh paine.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>This on my Tombe ſhall written bee, When I in Glory am with thee.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VAin mortals, you thinke I am dead,</l>
                     <l>You are deceiv'd, for I am fled.</l>
                     <l>Unto that Kingdome I did chuſe,</l>
                     <l>when as the earth I did refuſe.</l>
                     <l>And I in glory now am plac'ſt,</l>
                     <l>And with a Crowne in Heaven am grac'ſt.</l>
                     <l>My ſoul in fair bright Robes doth ſhine,</l>
                     <l>My Lord, methins they'r like to thine.</l>
                     <l>Which in the Mountain did appear</l>
                     <l>Glorious ſhining, bright and clear.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:169720:25"/>
                  <head>On marriage.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>LOrd! if thou haſt ordain'd for me,</l>
                     <l>That I on earth muſt married be:</l>
                     <l>As often I have been foretold,</l>
                     <l>Be not thy will, by me contrould.</l>
                     <l>And if my heart thou doſt incline</l>
                     <l>Children to have, Lord make them thine,</l>
                     <l>Or never let't be ſaid they'r mine.</l>
                     <l>I ſhall not like what's not divine.</l>
                     <l>I no ambition have for earth,</l>
                     <l>My thoughts are of a higher birth.</l>
                     <l>The Souls ſweet Babes, do bring no pain,</l>
                     <l>And they immortalize the name.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Gift.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>MY Lord, haſt thou given me away?</l>
                     <l>Did I on earth, for a gift ſtay?</l>
                     <l>Hath he by prayer of thee gain'd me,</l>
                     <l>Who was ſo ſtrictly knit to thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To thee I onely gave my heart,</l>
                     <l>Wouldſt thou my Lord from that giſt part?</l>
                     <l>I know thou wouldſt deliver me</l>
                     <l>To none, but one belov'd by thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But Lord my heart thou doſt not give,</l>
                     <l>Though here on earth, while I doe live</l>
                     <l>My body here he may retain,</l>
                     <l>My heart in heaven, with thee muſt reigne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:169720:25"/>
                     <l>Then as thy gift let him thinke me,</l>
                     <l>Sith I a donage am from thee.</l>
                     <l>And let him know thou haſt my heart,</l>
                     <l>He onely hath my earthly part.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It was my glory I was free,</l>
                     <l>And ſubject here to none but thee,</l>
                     <l>And ſtill that glory I ſhall hold</l>
                     <l>If thou my Spirit doſt infold.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It is my bliſſe, I here ſerve thee,</l>
                     <l>Tis my great joy; thou loveſt mee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The choice of my Friend.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>PRay tell the world, I did chuſe thee,</l>
                     <l>Cauſe thou aſpir'ſt to heaven with mee.</l>
                     <l>I did not chuſe for earthly ſtate,</l>
                     <l>But'cauſe thou ſeem'ſt baſe earth to hate.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It was not earth, my love did merit,</l>
                     <l>'Twas a high and heavenly ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>Thus with heaven, I did decree</l>
                     <l>That ſuch a one my friend ſhould be.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And while our ſpirits doe aſpire</l>
                     <l>To heaven, I have my hearts deſire,</l>
                     <l>And ſtill methinks I am yet free,</l>
                     <l>We living both great God in thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The change.</head>
                  <opener>Great God!</opener>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HOw haſt thou chang'd my thoughts in me,</l>
                     <l>For when I thought to be a wife,</l>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:169720:26"/>
                     <l>I then did think troubled to be,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe I ſaw moſt live in ſtrife<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But thou a husband haſt given me,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſweet diſcretion doth direct,</l>
                     <l>And orders all things ſo for me,</l>
                     <l>As if of heaven, he were elect.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To take all trouble quite from me,</l>
                     <l>That earths poſſeſſion here doth bring,</l>
                     <l>And ſo doth leave me quite to thee,</l>
                     <l>Thy praiſes here to ſit and ſing.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Promiſe Performed.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>MY Lord, thou haſt perform'd moſt free</l>
                     <l>What in thy word thou promis'd me.</l>
                     <l>That if thy Kingdome firſt ſought wee,</l>
                     <l>All things on earth ſhould added bee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou haſt giv'n me earth, water, aire,</l>
                     <l>And heavenly fire which is more rare,</l>
                     <l>That heavenly flame, thou haſt ſent me,</l>
                     <l>To offer up the earth to thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And if thou pleaſeſt them to take,</l>
                     <l>I willingly ſhall them forſake.</l>
                     <l>I'le not be loth to give to thee</l>
                     <l>What of thy bounty thou gav'ſt me.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Plenty thou haſt, great God in ſtore,</l>
                     <l>And if thou pleaſe canſt give me more.</l>
                     <l>If earth thou tak'ſt, and heaven giv'ſt me</l>
                     <l>A gainer yet, I much ſhall bee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:169720:26"/>
                  <head>Not a Husband, though never ſo excelling in goodneſs to us, muſt detaine our deſires from Heaven.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>MY heart I finde upon her wings,</l>
                     <l>Ready to flee from earthly things.</l>
                     <l>But that the vertue lives in thee,</l>
                     <l>On earth a while retaineth me.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not that of life I weary am,</l>
                     <l>For what on earth here wiſh I can,</l>
                     <l>From heavens great Prince, receive I doe,</l>
                     <l>I muſt moſt freely tell to you.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Great bleſſings from him I injoy,</l>
                     <l>And with him I have no annoy,</l>
                     <l>Yet theſe muſt not retaine my heart,</l>
                     <l>Another of me claims his part.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To heavens great prince I muſt away,</l>
                     <l>No love on earth here muſt me ſtay.</l>
                     <l>He lent me but awhile to you,</l>
                     <l>And now I muſt bid you adieu.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>My Deſcent.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IF any one thinke meane of me,</l>
                     <l>'Tis cauſe they doe not my birth ſee,</l>
                     <l>I did deſcend from a great King,</l>
                     <l>And an Immortall God did ſpring.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:169720:27"/>
                     <l>I'me daughter to the King of Kings,</l>
                     <l>And muſt contemn baſe earthly things.</l>
                     <l>To heaven's great Prince, he married me,</l>
                     <l>And now my linage you may ſee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And while I mean am in your eye,</l>
                     <l>I often to my glory flye,</l>
                     <l>And with my great Prince do abide,</l>
                     <l>Where placed by his bleſſed ſide.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>With heavenly bliſſe methinks I'me crown'd,</l>
                     <l>His glorious beams do me ſurround,</l>
                     <l>Where I ſet and hear the ſtory</l>
                     <l>Of my Prince, and ſee his glory.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>To my Husband.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHen from the world, I ſhall be tane,</l>
                     <l>And from earths neceſſary paine.</l>
                     <l>Then let no blacks be worne for me,</l>
                     <l>Not in a Ring my dear by thee.</l>
                     <l>But this bright Diamond, let it be</l>
                     <l>Worn in rememberance of me.</l>
                     <l>And when it ſparkles in your eye,</l>
                     <l>Think 'tis my ſhadow paſſeth by.</l>
                     <l>For why, more bright you ſhall me fee,</l>
                     <l>Then that or any Gem can bee.</l>
                     <l>Dreſs not the houſe with ſable weed,</l>
                     <l>As if there were ſome diſmall deed</l>
                     <l>Acted to be when I am gone,</l>
                     <l>There is no cauſe for me to mourn.</l>
                     <l>And let no badge of Herald be</l>
                     <l>The ſigne of my Antiquity.</l>
                     <l>It was my glory I did ſpring</l>
                     <l>From heavens eternall powerfull King:</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:169720:27"/>
                     <l>To his bright Palace heir am I.</l>
                     <l>It is his promiſe, hee'l not lye.</l>
                     <l>By my dear Brother pray lay me,</l>
                     <l>It was a promiſe made by thee,</l>
                     <l>And now I muſt bid thee adieu,</l>
                     <l>For I'me a parting now from you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>My Bill of thanks to <hi>Mr. C.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THough my words rare thou doſt not finde,</l>
                     <l>Might not God be prais'd by my minde.</l>
                     <l>The heart, not phraſe, God doth eſteem,</l>
                     <l>To him my heart in them are ſeen.</l>
                     <l>Let men, like God, my words, not minde</l>
                     <l>In them, a thankfull heart they finde.</l>
                     <l>To praiſe him is my ſouls intent,</l>
                     <l>For his great bleſſings he hath ſent.</l>
                     <l>You ſaid at the end of my dayes,</l>
                     <l>God would them bring out to my praiſe.</l>
                     <l>My own praiſe! I regard it not.</l>
                     <l>I have enough; God is my lot.</l>
                     <l>I would hear God now praiſed bee</l>
                     <l>For his great bleſſings giv'n to me.</l>
                     <l>You'ave bils of thanks oft ſent to you,</l>
                     <l>For earthly bleſſings, and they'r due.</l>
                     <l>Shall not then heavenly bleſſings be</l>
                     <l>More priz'd then earth; they ſhall by mee.</l>
                     <l>This Bill of thanks to you I ſend,</l>
                     <l>What though it be not rarely penn'd?</l>
                     <l>'Tis the intention of my heart,</l>
                     <l>That I in it to you impart,</l>
                     <l>It is not onely ſent to thee,</l>
                     <l>But Preachers all praiſe God for me.</l>
                     <l>I with a Trumpet could proclaime</l>
                     <l>Praiſes to the God of fame;</l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:169720:28"/>
                     <l>For teaching me to know his name,</l>
                     <l>All people for me doe the ſame.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Being in paine.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>LOrd, if my ſin produce my paine,</l>
                     <l>Pray let me never ſin againe.</l>
                     <l>For pain is grievous unto me,</l>
                     <l>And ſin is hatefull unto thee.</l>
                     <l>Let me not do what troubleth thee,</l>
                     <l>And thou'lt not ſend what grieve ſhall me.</l>
                     <l>But if my patience Lord thou tryeſt,</l>
                     <l>If I will bear, what thou applyeſt,</l>
                     <l>To cure the malady of ſin,</l>
                     <l>Ceaſe not my pain, but ſend't again;</l>
                     <l>For pain I rather would endure,</l>
                     <l>Then grieve thine eyes of light ſo pure.</l>
                     <l>That our moſt ſecret thoughts doe ſpie,</l>
                     <l>And wanton glances of the eye:</l>
                     <l>For which thou ſendeſt puniſhments,</l>
                     <l>Or elſe corrects with ſapience.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Being taken with a ſudden pain on the Day appointed for God's publick Service.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>LEt not this pain Lord, deter me</l>
                     <l>From publick offering praiſe to thee.</l>
                     <l>Though private prayers may pleaſing bee</l>
                     <l>From others, and as well from me.</l>
                     <l>But publick bleſſings thou giv'ſt me,</l>
                     <l>And publick praiſe I'de offer thee.</l>
                     <l>Thou te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt me, if I will confeſs</l>
                     <l>Thee before men; thou'lt do no leſſe</l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:169720:28"/>
                     <l>For me before thine Angels bright,</l>
                     <l>And thy great Father in his light.</l>
                     <l>In private I may ſerve thee here,</l>
                     <l>But that to men doth not appeare.</l>
                     <l>I then in publick will ſerve thee,</l>
                     <l>Whiles here thou giveſt me liberty.</l>
                     <l>And not depend on charity,</l>
                     <l>To think I doe belong to thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Antidote.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THis Antidote will cure your fear.</l>
                     <l>The God of heaven for you takes care.</l>
                     <l>They cannot fear, that live above,</l>
                     <l>Their fear is cured by their love.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>My Satisfaction.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I Am content with this earths fate,</l>
                     <l>Cauſe I am borne for higher ſtate.</l>
                     <l>Sweet quiet here I wiſh no more,</l>
                     <l>I'de have my glory kept in ſtore,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yet I have on thoſe Robes of glory,</l>
                     <l>Of which I oft have read the ſtory.</l>
                     <l>That pure refined ſouls doe wear,</l>
                     <l>Living in regions free from care.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For with the eye of faith I ſee</l>
                     <l>My ſelfe ſweet Prince, as I'me in thee:</l>
                     <l>And with thee I doe live above,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe we live where we doe love.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:169720:29"/>
                  <p>But Oh my God! when ſhall it be that the dark Lanthorne of Faith, ſhall be ſwallowed up in the bright mantle of ſweet fruition?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Being called a Stoick</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>NOt as a Stoick I'me exempt from care,</l>
                     <l>But as a Chriſtian I would all things beare.</l>
                     <l>Nor that I blinded am and nothing ſee,</l>
                     <l>No: I ſee all, but take all patiently.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Gods Prerogative.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>LOrd, ſhall I grudge at thy juſt will,</l>
                     <l>Or ſhall I queſtion thy great skill,</l>
                     <l>And think the world thou doſt not rule</l>
                     <l>As thou art wont; peace ſilly fool.</l>
                     <l>Without his rule it cannot ſtand,</l>
                     <l>All things are done at his command.</l>
                     <l>Doe not then grudge at what he doth,</l>
                     <l>Nor in thy heart have any ruth</l>
                     <l>Gainſt them who now do rule the Land,</l>
                     <l>They have no power but from his hand.</l>
                     <l>The earth is his, and he plucks down</l>
                     <l>Who him diſpleaſe, and gives the Crowne</l>
                     <l>To others, if they him obey,</l>
                     <l>They ſhall ſtill rule; if not, then they</l>
                     <l>Shall be deſtroyed with his frown,</l>
                     <l>And to their foes hee'l give their Crown,</l>
                     <l>Then let me Lord my ſelfe ſubmit</l>
                     <l>To what thy wiſdom ſeeth fit.</l>
                     <l>Sith no authority can be,</l>
                     <l>But what appointed is by thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:169720:29"/>
                  <head>My Manſion.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>ELiza</hi> for, doe you not care,</l>
                     <l>She lives in heaven, free from earths feare,</l>
                     <l>Her 'bidings in thoſe regions be,</l>
                     <l>Her converſe with the Deity.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Mans unkindneſſe my Benefit.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>LOrd, what a courteſie doth man to me,</l>
                     <l>When he's unkind, he drives me ſtraight to thee.</l>
                     <l>Where I my deer ſweet Prince, do ever finde</l>
                     <l>Carefull for me, contenting, pleaſing, kinde.</l>
                     <l>Then let them be, as liketh them to me,</l>
                     <l>'Ile not complain, ſith I can come to thee,</l>
                     <l>Who art my joy, my love, my crown, my peace,</l>
                     <l>In whom my joys abound, and ſtill increaſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>My Second Part.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I Did withdraw me from the ſtage</l>
                     <l>Of this vain world, in my beſt age.</l>
                     <l>Thinking for heaven thou hadſt bedreſt,</l>
                     <l>So I retired for my reſt.</l>
                     <l>But thou a Prophet hadſt me made</l>
                     <l>Unto my ſelfe when I had ſaid.</l>
                     <l>Another part I here muſt play,</l>
                     <l>Before I went from hence away.</l>
                     <l>A wife thou choo'ſt out for my part,</l>
                     <l>Which I miſliked in my heart;</l>
                     <l>And thought wedded to none to bee</l>
                     <l>Great Prince of Heaven and earth but thee.</l>
                     <l>But thou that hadſt ordain'd that part,</l>
                     <l>Foundſt' out a means to turne my heart:</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:169720:30"/>
                     <l>Becauſe my Lord, thou'lt have me ſee</l>
                     <l>We happy in that life may be,</l>
                     <l>But then on thee, we muſt depend,</l>
                     <l>For thou alone that bliſſe canſt ſend.</l>
                     <l>For ſhould our Husbands love fixt be</l>
                     <l>Upon ſome others, not on thee.</l>
                     <l>Heavens Prince will never thee forſake,</l>
                     <l>But ſtill his darling will thee make.</l>
                     <l>And ſhould hee of thee careleſſe bee,</l>
                     <l>Heavens Prince, he will more carefull bee.</l>
                     <l>He from the earth wil raiſe thy heart,</l>
                     <l>That thou content maiſt act that part.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Reſurrection.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHy ſhould I be afraid to dye,</l>
                     <l>Or let my body in earth lye.</l>
                     <l>In that ſaſe bed I'me laid to ſleep,</l>
                     <l>When others in their cloſets weep.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It is to me a quiet night,</l>
                     <l>And next day brings the wiſhed light,</l>
                     <l>That makes for me eternall day,</l>
                     <l>My body there feels no decay.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And when I waken, I ſhall finde</l>
                     <l>All things well pleaſing to my minde.</l>
                     <l>Youth, beauty, ſpirit, now preſent</l>
                     <l>Themſelves for that days Ornament.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>With Robes more bright then are the beams,</l>
                     <l>That from her pleaſing Sun here ſtreams,</l>
                     <l>Decay they ſay they never will,</l>
                     <l>For they were made with exact skill,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:169720:30"/>
                     <l>To adorne the bodies that aſcend,</l>
                     <l>And on the Deity attend,</l>
                     <l>Now ſhall I ſee my Princely peer,</l>
                     <l>That I on earth did hold ſo deer.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And with him ſtill converſe ſhall I,</l>
                     <l>Who would not now let their ſoul fly,</l>
                     <l>Seing there's no fear of decay,</l>
                     <l>Fools that think death a diſmall day.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Fearfull <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>OH you that know not when you dye,</l>
                     <l>Whither your Souls to heaven ſhall fly,</l>
                     <l>Or wander, in the diſmall ſhade,</l>
                     <l>No wonder though you be afraid.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Would you not wear black helliſh weeds?</l>
                     <l>Avoid then, wicked ſinfull deeds.</l>
                     <l>Do actions that are juſt and right,</l>
                     <l>If you would live in heavenly light.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Do you think peace you can enjoy,</l>
                     <l>That others with your deeds annoy?</l>
                     <l>No! what you unto others doe</l>
                     <l>Aſſure your ſelves, ſhall fall on you.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And if good councell, now you ſlight</l>
                     <l>Look in Hells mouth, and be affright.</l>
                     <l>Avoid betimes, that helliſh fume,</l>
                     <l>Which all your pleaſures will conſume.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:169720:31"/>
                  <head>To Generall Cromwell.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe Sword of God doth ever well</l>
                     <l>I'th hand of vertue! O Cromwel,</l>
                     <l>But why doe I, complain of thee?</l>
                     <l>'Cauſe thou'rt the rod that ſcourgeth mee?</l>
                     <l>But if a good child I will bee,</l>
                     <l>I'le kiſs the Rod, and honour thee;</l>
                     <l>And if thou'rt vertuous as 'tis ſed,</l>
                     <l>Thou'lt have the glory when thou'rt dead.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sith Kings and Princes ſcourged be,</l>
                     <l>Whip thou the Lawyer from his fee</l>
                     <l>That is ſo great, when nought they doe,</l>
                     <l>And we are put off from our due.</l>
                     <l>But they for their excuſe do ſay,</l>
                     <l>'Tis from the Law is our delay.</l>
                     <l>By Tyrants heads thoſe laws were made,</l>
                     <l>As by the learned it is ſaid.</l>
                     <l>If then from Tyrants you'l us free,</l>
                     <l>Free us from their Laws Tyranny.</l>
                     <l>If not! wee'l ſay the head is pale,</l>
                     <l>But ſtill the ſting lives in the tail.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>To a Lady that bragg'd of her Children.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IF thou haſt cauſe to joy in thine,</l>
                     <l>I have cauſe too to joy of mine.</l>
                     <l>Thine did proceed from ſinfull race,</l>
                     <l>Mine from the heavenly dew of grace.</l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:169720:31"/>
                     <l>Thine at their birth did pain thee bring,</l>
                     <l>When mine are borne, I ſet and ſing.</l>
                     <l>Thine doth delight in nought but ſin,</l>
                     <l>My Babes work is, to praiſe heav'ns King.</l>
                     <l>Thine bring both ſorrow, pain and fear,</l>
                     <l>Mine baniſh from me dreadfull care.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>The Conqueſt.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>GOd made on earth a paradice at firſt,</l>
                     <l>For man, but he by ſin betrayd his truſt.</l>
                     <l>But heavens great Prince who came to conquer ſin,</l>
                     <l>For me won Heaven and Paradiſe againe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Queſtions and Anſwers.</head>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>LOrd! why have I ſo much from thee?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Th'art child to me.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>But why on earth have I ſuch ſtore?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> In Heav'n is more.</p>
                  <p>Qu. <hi>Lord I have more then I doe need?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> The poor then feed.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then ſith l'me thine,</l>
                     <l>I'le be divine,</l>
                     <l>And what I've more.</l>
                     <l>I'le give the poor.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:169720:32"/>
                  <head>To a Friend for her Naked Breaſts.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>MAdam I praiſe you, 'cauſe you'r free,</l>
                     <l>And you doe not conceal from me</l>
                     <l>What hidden in your heart doth lye,</l>
                     <l>If I can it through your breaſts ſpy.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Some Ladies will not ſhow their breaſts,</l>
                     <l>For feare men think they are undreſt,</l>
                     <l>Or by't their hearts they ſhould diſcover,</l>
                     <l>They do't to tempt ſome wanton Lover.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>They are afraid tempters to be,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe a Curſe impos'd they ſee,</l>
                     <l>Upon the tempter that was firſt,</l>
                     <l>By an all-ſeeing God that's juſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But though I praiſe you have a care</l>
                     <l>Of that al-ſeeing eye, and feare,</l>
                     <l>Leſt he through your bare breſts ſee ſin,</l>
                     <l>And puniſh you for what's within.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Safety.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>MY gracious God be not my foe,</l>
                     <l>It matters not if man be ſo.</l>
                     <l>And let my wayes great God pleaſe thee,</l>
                     <l>Then from all foes I ſhall be free.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:169720:32"/>
                  <head>What Kingdome to be wiſht.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHoſe Kingdome can I wiſh but thine,</l>
                     <l>Who mak'ſt hell, Heaven and me divine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What Kingdome ought I wiſh to be,</l>
                     <l>But where all thine ſhall reign with thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All thoughts of Kingdoms I will baniſh,</l>
                     <l>But of thy Kingdome will not vaniſh.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No Kingdome muſt I wiſh,</l>
                     <l>But Heav'ns great Prince of glory,</l>
                     <l>Which if I be divine,</l>
                     <l>Will be mine onely ſtory.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Earthly bleſſings doe me ſurround,</l>
                     <l>With heavenly bleſſings I am crown'd.</l>
                     <l>On earth I live free from all care.</l>
                     <l>Becauſe heavens King I love and feare.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Comfort in Temptations and Afflictions.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>COme Chriſtians that ſo mazed bee</l>
                     <l>At earths events, O come and ſee</l>
                     <l>What cauſe there is for your diſmay,</l>
                     <l>When God takes care for you each day.</l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:169720:33"/>
                     <l>Th'Apoſtle bids us then to joy,</l>
                     <l>When as temptations us annoy.</l>
                     <l>And heavens great Prince ſed unto you</l>
                     <l>Before, he bid the earth adieu.</l>
                     <l>Let not your hearts here troubled be,</l>
                     <l>For if you do beleeve on me,</l>
                     <l>In heav'n a Palace there is for you,</l>
                     <l>Fear not, in me, it is your due.</l>
                     <l>I'ſt priſon that doth you afright?</l>
                     <l>In dungeon deep hee'l be your light.</l>
                     <l>I'ſt war whoſe fear you do pretend?</l>
                     <l>The Lord of Hoſt can you defend.</l>
                     <l>I'ſt ſicknes that doth cauſe your dread?</l>
                     <l>He eaſie can make your ſick bed.</l>
                     <l>Unleſs by theſe he will you take</l>
                     <l>Into his glory, and there make</l>
                     <l>You to behold thoſe Viſions fair,</l>
                     <l>Will raviſh you from all your care.</l>
                     <l>Then ſith heav'ns King can ſafe you keep,</l>
                     <l>There is no cauſe for you to weep.</l>
                     <l>You ſhall not enter to his reſt,</l>
                     <l>If you be doubting him moleſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>On going to the Sacrament.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I To the world Lord will let know,</l>
                     <l>That I deſire thy death to ſhow;</l>
                     <l>By going to ſome publick place,</l>
                     <l>And take the pledges of thy grace.</l>
                     <l>And when I take the bread, then I</l>
                     <l>Will ſay, my Lord did for me dye.</l>
                     <l>And thus Ile doe great God for thee,</l>
                     <l>For thou haſt done much more for mee;</l>
                     <l>And when I drinke the wine Ile tell</l>
                     <l>Thy blood redeem'd my ſoul from hell;</l>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:169720:33"/>
                     <l>And then Ile offer up to thee</l>
                     <l>What thou ſweet Prince! requireſt of me.</l>
                     <l>None but the Sacrifice of praiſe</l>
                     <l>Doſt thou require now adayes,</l>
                     <l>And that I ſhould remember thee,</l>
                     <l>When as theſe things are done by mee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="meditations">
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>My Prayer in my Youth.</head>
                  <p>MY Lord, whoſe mercies to me are unſpeakable; who in thy works art great and powerfull, wholly bend mine affection on that which is certain, and not ſubject to varibility; to that which to that which no ſiniſter miſhap can alter; Oh, let not my Soul which thou haſt made to be fed with heavenly Manna (which ſtill will laſt) here ſeek to be ſatisfied with vain delights, which ſoon will vaniſh. Baniſh from me the Thoughts of vaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, and make me know that they muſt end. And for thoſe infinite bleſſings which thou haſt deigned to beſtow upon me, make me for ever to admire thee, and from my heart ſend up the ſweet incenſe of thanks and praiſe for thy heavenly benefits beſtowed on me thine unworthy ſervant.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>The Temptation.</head>
                  <p>MY Soul! Woulſt thou finde favour with the Lord, be not then afraid to goe to him; Let not the feare of thy former paſt ſins, nor of thy continuall weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs be an occaſion to hinder thee of thy happineſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but let the aſſurance of the pardon of thy ſins, and the certainty of the promiſe to ſtrengthen thy weakneſs, animate thee to goe confidently to the throne of grace. There do not imagine that thou ſeeſt thy ſins ſtand as
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169720:34"/> a thick cloud to keep thy prayers from aſcending to the preſence of thy God, nor think that through that dark cloud thou ſeem'ſt unſeemly in the eyes of thy loving father; be not thou ignorant that the bright beames of his gracious favour, hath diſperſed thoſe clouds of thy ſins, never to be gathered again together, before his pure eyes. Know thou, that he will not let ſuch fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſights, and ſad appearances, to ſtand in his preſence, to afright his dear choſen children; No my Soul! ſuch ſights are not there; he that cals thee hath removed from thee all thoſe things which ſhould hinder thy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to him; or diſturbe thy quiet appearance, before him. He cals thee, and bids thee be confident in his preſence; He aſſured thee by his word that thou ſhalt finde his ſpirit ſtrengthning thy weakneſs, and inabling thee to performe that which thou thoughteſt impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for thee to overcome.</p>
                  <p>My Soul! he hath brought thee from thy ſtraying er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, he hath inabled thee to overcome the manifold temptations of thy ſuttle enemy, when he would have made thee to have thought there was no God, then thy God manifeſted himſelf to thee, when he would have had thee taken pleaſure in the vaine delights of this wicked world, then thy dear father having a watchfull eye, and a carefull minde over thee, ſent a heavy dulnes into all the powers of thy ſoul &amp; body, inforcing thee as it were to leave thoſe earthly vaniſhes, becauſe neither ſoul nor body could take delight in thoſe things, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers call pleaſures. by reaſon of thy exceeding heavy dulneſs. Then doſt thou my ſoul, think that a moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere puniſhment on thee from thy father, when thou ſaweſt others injoy the bleſſings of thy God with great contentment: Then in the height of this diſtemper wert thou my ſoul almoſt brought to the pit of deſpair. When as the enemy pictur'd before the eyes of thy ſoul, the ſad appearance of the anger of thy God, and ſtill he
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169720:34"/> perſiſting in his pernicious temptations, bid thee leave his ſervice, telling thee it was to no purpoſe to be ſo carefull to ſerve him, for thy prayers were not heard, thy tears not regarded, thy heavineſs not removed; and if Gods word be true, he hears all that cals upon him, and removeth from them their griefs. Thus ſubtly delt my enemy with me, thinking to havein wrapt me in his hidden nets of moſt pernicious temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. Firſt, making me to think my God was angry, then that he heard not my prayers, and that his word was falfe: thus by conſequence faine would he have made me to have doubted of thy being, O my eternall and ever-being Father. By theſe ſnares would he have bereft me of the hope I had in thy word, by which I was brought to know thee. Thy creatures teach us (I acknowledge O Lord) to know that there is a God, but they cannot teach us to know how to come to this God, or how to finde comfort in thee our God; 'tis onely thy word can declare to us what thou art, and thy ſpirit it is that muſt aſſure us, that this word is thine. It was thy ſelfe O Lord, who art able to performe what thou haſt decreed, that haſt brought this flinty heart of mine to the knowledge of thee. My Lord, I muſt needs confeſs thy powerfull working in framing this heart of mine to the belief of thy word, and thee; for before thy ſpirit mollified this heart of mine, thy word was to it like water gliding over the hardeſt marble, no whit entring or piercing the ſame.</p>
                  <p>My gracious Lord, thy divine Majeſty in all the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and chances of my life, hath had a moſt peculiar care of me, for now haſt thou taught me to know, that thoſe temptations, and thoſe perplexities, in which my ſoul was in, have been all diſpoſed for the good and happineſs of my Soul. Now thou makeſt me to know that thy word is true, and that our grief doth work for our good: for though our temptations be never ſo
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169720:35"/> great, thou canſt and wilt deliver thy children.</p>
                  <p>It was thy Majeſty that kept me from doubting of thy being; it was thy fatherly goodnes that ſtupified the powers of my Soul and Body with that heavy dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, not becauſe thou wouldeſt puniſh me for my ſins, no! thou didſt teach me to know, that my gracious Saviour had already indur'd the puniſhment that my ſins deſerv'd; My Lord, thy Majeſty did not lay that dejection on me proceeding from thy juſtice, but thy mercy. For my God! I muſt confeſs to thee, that which thou then didſt know, for then I did love the world, more then I loved thee, and becauſe thou wouldſt have me love the pleaſure that ſhould never end; thou madſt me to take no pleaſure in theſe delights, which never end but in ſorrow. That heavineſs was then a bitter pill to purge my Soul from the groſſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of earthly love, that afterwards ſhe may be made more fit and apt to receive the ſweet bliſſe of thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting love. This thy love to me kept me from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into the miſerable pit of deſpaire; thy loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe it was that moved thee to let that word of comfort with which thou ſuſtaineſt thy ſervant St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſound ever in my ears, That thy grace ſhould be ſufficient for me without which grace of thine, I not having ſufficient ſtrength of my ſelf, ſhould have fallen into the gulf of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting miſery. Thy love likewiſe kept me conſtant to thee and thy ſervice, &amp; kept me from doing or ſaying that in my diſpairing thoughts, that had not been fit for thy ſervant to doe or utter. Thy unwearied love and great wiſdome it was that ſent thoſe tryals and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to me in my youth, that thou mighteſt ſanctifie my youth to thy ſervice, and make me careleſſe of thoſe pleaſures, that my young years were too much addicted to.</p>
                  <p>For if thy Majeſty had ſuffered me to have run on, to have taken pleaſure in thoſe vanities, till I had been in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169720:35"/> wrapt in them, and had ſet my whole delight in thoſe vaniſhing pleaſures. Then had it been more hard and grievous to me to have left them; But thou, O my Lord, didſt deal more graciouſly with me; for before I knew what pleaſures meant, thou took'ſt from me the love of pleaſure, for which great mercy of thine, I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thee moſt hearty thanks.</p>
                  <p>My Lord! When I conſider of theſe thine infinite mercies, I cannot chuſe but admire thy goodneſs, and admiring, ſay unto thy heavenly Majeſty. O Lord, what am I that thou ſhouldeſt have ſuch a peculiar care of me; I am not worthy to be in thy thoughts, much more unworthy to be belov'd of thee; yet it doth evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appear that thou doſt love me, in that thou ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keſt off from me the love of the world; for my Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unleſs thou loveſt me, thou wouldeſt not have cared for my love, and I know that it was in love that thou wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſt me from the world, becauſe that I ſhould love thee alone, and not the world.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>The Angels Joy.</head>
                  <p>YOu bleſſed Angels, by my Father are we honoured to have you for our attendance. Sure your lovely faces could not but look ſad when my Saviour ſuffered: for methinks it was a ſad ſight to behold, your loving Lord hang tormented on a curſed tree, and for thoſe too, whoſe ſins cauſed his torment; and then for you to hear him cry out in the bitterneſs of his Soul, <hi>My God, my God, Why haſt thou forſaken mee?</hi> Methinks it ſhould have ſo incens'd your wrath againſt us poor mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall creatures, that you ſhould have petitioned to your All-powerfull Lord; that all humane fleſh ſhould have
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169720:36"/> ſuffered endleſſe torment, ſeeing they had ſo juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it, rather then your righteous Lord ſhould have dyed.</p>
                  <p>But whether my Soul; in the deep conſideration of the undeſerved ſuffering of thy righteous Saviour doſt thou run? Shall the Angels which are our attendants be grieved at our happineſſe? My Soul, wrong not thoſe bleſſed ſpirits with ſuch vain thoughts; for God was not pleaſed, nor his wrath appeaſed towards us till that time: Oh ſad time, yet pleaſant time, the time of thy moſt gracious dying: Sad, in reſpect of thy torments, O bleſſed Saviour; yet pleaſant in reſpect of the unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſable liberty, and endleſs happineſs, which by thy powerfull dying we obtain'd.</p>
                  <p>Oh Bleſſed Spirits, I cannot now thinke, that you were diſpleas'd with us, for your nature doth ſo concur with his will, that it cannot be oppoſite to it.</p>
                  <p>But yet God was angry; yea, to the very apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his onely Son, What elſe made him cry out ſo grievouſly, <hi>My God, Why haſt thou forſaken mee?</hi> God was angry then with his Son, for us; you had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then of grief for him, not anger towards him: but yet ſure to ſee him angry with his Son, and to ſee his onely Son ſo grievouſly tormented, you could not but be mov'd, what then muſt move you? ſure it could be nothing, but our ſins for which he ſuffered.</p>
                  <p>Oh you heavenly Spirits. I finde you rejoycing, when we had our Saviour born, and ſure you could not but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, when the worke of our ſalvation was finiſhed, your joy was then intermingled with your ſorrow, if you be capable of ſorrow, for you could not but ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, to ſee your God ſo grievouſly to ſuffer; you could not but rejoyce, to ſee that they on whom you atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſhould be ſo happy, that by his death they ſhould be admitted to injoy eternall life.</p>
                  <p>If you joy at our repentance, ſure your joy at our
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169720:36"/> forgiveneſſe, and then was the time of our forgiveneſſe come, when he willingly yeelded up his life, that we might live eternally, then was our debts paid, when as thy now glorified body, Oh Son of glory, was debar'd of the heavenly appearance, of thine eternall God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</p>
                  <p>Yee bleſſed Angels, yee joyed in your ſorrow, and not we, but our ſins were hatefull to you, which were the cauſe of his moſt grievous ſuffering.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>More bitter then grim death could be,</l>
                     <l>My ſin, my Lord was unto thee,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe I ſinn'd my Lord did dye,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe he dy'd, hate ſin will I.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>On Earthly Love.</head>
                  <p>FRom thee, O Heaven of glorie flowes that celeſtiall ſtream, that being taken hath power to make us forgetfull of our earthly love, the which muſt vaniſh, and alone can ſet us free from thoſe tormenting paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſweet ſtream, having cur'd us of thoſe diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered paſſions, haſt then the power to work in our hearts a more peaceable and durable affection: earthly affection, ever brings diſtemper, ſometimes diſtraction; but that ſweet love, which thou O pearly fountain, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt in our breaſt, flameth in our hearts, peace, reſt, joy, and it worketh a perpetuall aſſurance of ſtill injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what we love, wiſh, or can in heart deſire.</p>
                  <p>My Lord! My ſoule is raviſht with the contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy heavenly love; and I cannot chuſe but infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely admire thy mercies to me thine unworthy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169720:37"/> for grievous were the perturbations which I was ſubject to, when I was infected with the poiſon-bane of earthly affections, the which a time thou wert pleas'd to let reigne and tyrannize in my breſt, which like a thorne in the fleſh, not being drawne out, by the hand of art, lies throbbing and working torment, not onely to the place where it hath taken up its abode, but brings diſtemper to the whole body: So that unruly paſſion ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken up his place in my heart, did not onely ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannize there, but wrought deſtraction in my Soul, and bred diſtemper in my body; But bleſſed be thy Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie for that diſtemper, for in that time of my weaknes, thou Oh all-powerfull hand, by thy moſt heavenly art, didſt draw from my heart that tormenting paſſion, and by the addition of thy heavenly love, which thou didſt leave in the room thereof; thou repairedſt in me the breaches that that unrulie paſſion had made.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When I was ſick I thought that I ſhould dye,</l>
                     <l>I did miſtake, 'twas earthly love, not I.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>HOSEA 2. 19.</head>
                  <head type="sub">My Contract.</head>
                  <p>MY Lord! Doth not thy Majeſtie ſend thy meſſages of love and favour, to thoſe that will take hold of them, and beleeve there ſhall be a performance of what is promis'd, Thy Word tels us, <hi>That they that beleeve in thee ſhall have eternall life:</hi> My Lord, I do beleeve it, and that this Meſſage, ſent by thy royal Embaſſador, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169720:37"/> to mee, aſwell as to any other; [I will marry thee to mee for ever] Thou art righteous and wilt perform it; who would now refuſe ſo great, and ſo good a King? I diſdain not marriage, I deſire it with this great Prince, who is the Prince of Kings, and at whoſe foot-ſtool they muſt one day lay down all their Crowns, and bring in all their riches at his command: The greateſt of them muſt confeſs they hold their Scepters of him, and to him they muſt doe ſervice, at his will. This is a Prince of ſuch exact perfection, that I cannot ſee any thing in him any way to be diſlik't. When I conſider any creature, I can finde in it but little to be belov'd, but a great deal of inconvenience with it, to be diſlik't; why then ſhould I ſet my minde on the creature of ſo little worth? and not wholly have my minde intent on the Creator, who alone is excellent. Moſt mighty Prince, I muſt confeſs my ſelf unworthy to be the leaſt ſervant in the Court of ſo magnificent a King; much leſſe to be one who ſhall have the honour to be marryed to thee; but becauſe I doe thinke my ſelfe unworthy of thee, ſhall I be ſuch a fool to refuſe ſo great a fortune? No, I will not. My Lord! I now challenge thy promiſe, for I doe think thou haſt prepared me a minde for thy ſelfe, for thou madſt me long ſince to be ambitious of perfection, but when I ſaw it was not to bee obtain'd in this world, how ſlightly did I eſteem of all things in it? thou having prepared my mind for thy ſelf, by the diſlike of all imperfect creatures, and the love of perfection, Thou madſt me to ſee a clear perfection in thy ſelf, and wroughſt in me a love to thee; and becauſe I dare not preſume to the thoughts of poſſeſſing thee, thou ſeeing my deſires, ſent that comfortable meſſage to me, and to all that doe ſincerely love thee, that thou wil receive us to thy ſelfe, and wilt marry us to thee for ever.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I being wedded to Heavens King,</l>
                     <l>As his bleſt Spouſe muſt his praiſe ſing.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:169720:38"/>
                  <head>The Soules Agitation.</head>
                  <p>MY great and glorious God! In what a ſtrange agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is my Soul, being aſſail'd by two contrary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations; the one of my heavenly bliſs, in which thou didſt at firſt make me, and to which thou haſt and wilt, in the fulneſs of time againe reſtore me; the other of the fordid and vile condition, in which I had by my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion inwrapt my ſelfe. The thoughts of the firſt fils me with a ſweet contenting joy; the conſideration of the other with a hatefull deteſtation of my ſelfe; for when I record in my minde, how thou at the firſt mad'ſt me a creature of a rare compoſition, one part of thine owne divine ſpirit, the other of earth purified, by thy heavenly art, and built up fit for a Temple for thy divine greatneſſe to inhabite; theſe thoughts fill me with a pleaſing contentment. But when the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my vile condition, in which by my too much yeelding to pleaſe my earthly companion, comes into my minde, I then hate my ſelfe, for I have thereby made my ſelf ſubject to all painfull diſeaſes, yea, to mortality, by my intemperance; for how juſtly might I have pleas'd my ſelfe in the lawfull and temperate uſe of all thy other creatures; and could not a whole world of pleaſures content us, but we muſt take that one for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden? My God! I am to my ſelfe, a hatefull crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, how much more muſt I needs be to thee, whoſe eyes can behold no impurity? but my dear Father look not now on me as I have cloath'd my ſelf, but look on me as new arrai'd by thy bleſſed Son, the King of Saints.</p>
                  <p>And to ſettle the diſturbed motion of my mind, ſend
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169720:38"/> downe a beam from thy glorious divinity, that might ſo inlighten the eyes of my Soul, that I might now behold my ſelfe, as cloathed with thy ſelf, for thou wert pleas'd to cloath thy divine nature with my mortality; that my mortall nature might be made immortall, by being joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to thy divinity. My great God! theſe thoughts will not onely take off my hatred from my ſelf, but I fear, if it be poſſible, make me too much love and admire my ſelfe: but it cannot be; for that bright beame from thee, makes me ſee my ſelfe, not but in thee, and with theſe thoughts haſt thou ſo rais'd my Soul beyond what it was, that I ſee my ſelf cloath'd with the bright white robes of thy pure innocence; for thou knoweſt no ſin. I now look on my ſelfe as ſacred, and on this fleſh as immortall, onely becauſe it hath ſpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ted it ſelfe with ſin, after thou hadſt made it purer then the common earth; therefore in the earth muſt it be laid again to be purified till it be fit to be new built up a glorious ſtructure for her divine companion: Then wilt thou take us both up into thy glorious habitation, where we ſhall not be capable of doing any thing that ſhall any more cauſe us to part from our ſelves or thee.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I once immortall was Lord! made by thee,</l>
                     <l>I that bliſs loſt; But I againe it ſee:</l>
                     <l>Reſtor'd with more, great Prince of Saints to me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>The Contempt of the World.</head>
                  <p>MY Gracious God! Doe I offend thee, if I contemn the world? I finde thy bleſt Apoſtle counting all
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169720:39"/> but dung in reſpect of the knowledge of thee; then by his example I hope I offend thee not; but yet, when I conſider it is thy workman-ſhip, which is moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, and thou haſt given it to the ſons of men, I cannot but call my thoughts in queſtion with ſome ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition of fear of offending thee; for my dear God! I confeſs, that what I ſee moſt deſired by people, for themſelves or for others, is to me moſt diſpleaſing and diſtaſtefull. My powerfull God! if I doe not offend thee in it, ſtill keep me in this minde; if I doe, root out (as it is my daily prayer) this contempt, and all things elſe that within me diſliketh the pure eyes of thy divine Majeſty.</p>
                  <p>My Lord! Somewhat to clear my ſelfe to the world, that I doe not offend in this point (for thou knoweſt my heart) I doe not contemn any thing in it, as thinking meanly of it, as thou hadſt made it; My great God! thou madeſt all things good at the beginning, but ſince the making of them, the perfection of all things is much changed. Our ſins altered the purity of all things in the world; then as it is made ſordid, by our ſins, I diſtaſte thoſe odde things I ſee pleaſing to the moſt.</p>
                  <p>But my Lord! This may draw me into another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience, and make ſome thinke, I thinke better of my ſelfe then of others, for diſtaſting thoſe things ſully<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſin; But I know thou wilt anſwer for me, that I confeſs to thee that by nature I am ſinfull, addicted to love thoſe things ſoyled by our ſins; ſo that it doth not make me think well of my ſelf, but it makes me love and admire thee the more; when I ſee thy abundant mercy to me, in giving me a minde, ſo contrary to the moſt; for I doubt not but thou haſt made many in the world as happy as thou haſt made me, in giving them ſuch a minde; For my deare Father! What do they atchieve when they attaine that here which they deſire, a few conveniences, accompanied with ten thouſand troubles,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169720:39"/> fears, and diſtaſtefull cares; for I have often heard ſome expreſs, how happy they ſhould be but for ſuch and ſuch inconveniences, when I having food and raiment ſufficient, and poſſeſſe a heaven of felicity in thee, am happy without a <hi>But.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>The Royal Gods.</head>
                  <p>MY Lord! With what a Title haſt thou honored the Kings of the earth: <hi>I have ſaid yee are Gods; and the Children of the moſt high.</hi> Thou haſt given them that Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle their deſires pretended too, to be Gods, and to be of their race, they that knew not thee, my great God! nor from what true immortall race they ſprung; yet would have the world think them to be of divine linage, and themſelves to be gods. And ſhall not wee, who know from whom and by whom Kings reigne, think our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be as they are ſtil'd by that great King, who ſet them to reigne for him? God forbid, but that we ſhould ſo think of them, and they of themſelves. He is the great God of the world, and hath ſet them as leſſer Gods un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, to governe and protect that people over which he hath plac'ſt them. The people muſt then honor their King, as a God under him, not obſerve or adore him above him; and hee muſt eſteem himſelfe as a God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; if he be of that great immortall race he will not degenerate, but will be like to him: He will be like a fiery pillar in the night of ignorance and darkneſſe, to direct them which way they ſhall walk; and as a cloud in the day of perſecution, to keep them from the purſuing adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary: he will my God with thee hide them under his wings, and they ſhall be ſafe under his protection: hee will be juſt too; puniſhing thoſe who ſeek the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169720:40"/> of thine and his people. His bowels of mercy will be extended, and he will not puniſh according to their deſerts; and rather then deſtruction ſhall ſhall come to thine and their people, they will follow the example of that renowned Prince, thy firſt-born Son, they will with him a while leave their glory, and take up with him an humble deportment, and cry with him, <hi>Thy will be done not mine:</hi> They thus imitating thee, their great patterne, ſhall be bleſſedt by thee with eternall renown, and crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by thee in immortal glory: but firſt thou haſt ſaid, <hi>They muſt dye like men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>The Rule.</head>
                  <p>MY Lord! What an infallible rule haſt thou left us, to know, whether we be thine or no; for if the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel of our bleſſed Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> be to us fooliſhneſſe, and as a thing we delight not in, we may juſtly feare we are to periſh: but if it be eſteem'd by us the power and excellent wiſdom of God, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights our hearts; we may be confident we ſhall be ſav'd; for the preaching of the Goſpel is to them that periſh fooliſhneſſe, but to us that are ſaved it is the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>PSALME 119. 165.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The Soules Peace.</head>
                  <p>MY great God! how often doſt thou make us to ſee, and by experience to know the truth of thy moſt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169720:40"/> ſacred Word, 'tis great peace indeed, that they poſſeſſe who love thy law: thou keepeſt them in ſuch ſecure and pleaſant pavillions, that nothing ſhall ofiend them, they muſt ſpeak to thy praiſe, whom thou haſt bleſt, and if I have been thought too mean to ſpeake in the praiſe of an earthly King; My God, I cannot but confeſs my ſelf too mean, too ignorant to ſpeak off, and in the praiſe of the Majeſty of Heaven.</p>
                  <p>But Oh thou greateſt and higheſt Ruler of all the Great on earth, under whoſe feet lye all their crownes of Majeſty: Thou haſt told us thou art to reſpector of perſons, but thou accepteſt of the prayers and praiſes of thy meaneſt creatures. Then muſt my Soul ſpeak to the praiſe of thy Sacred Majeſty, for the peace that thou haſt given mee, ſince the time that thou haſt taught mee to love thy Law; thou haſt made me to delight in the multitude of peace, thou haſt given me peace in thee, thy bleſſed Son ſet me at peace with thee, and I have ſuch a peace in thee, that all the oppſition of the world cannot take from me. I am at peace with thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, I am ſure they will not hurt me; I am at peace with thy creatures, for thou haſt made the ſtones, and beaſts af the field to be at league with them that feare thy name; I paſſe by thy creatures, and thorow them without fear, for they are at peace with me.</p>
                  <p>But canſt thou my Soul ſay, thou thus poſſeſſeſt a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py peace withall No, I cannot: for then they that have ſought to diſturbe my peace, by their odd untruths, will tell me, I ſaid not true; for I have ſeen and felt their Arrows of uncivill war ſtrike againſt my heart: But my God thou haſt ſo ſtrongly arm'd it, that their arrows have recoyl'd back, and not pierc'd my heart: How can I chuſe then moſt bleſſed and ſweet finger of <hi>Iſrael</hi> but ſpeak in thy own words;</p>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:169720:41"/>
                     <l>Great peace and reſt ſhall all ſuch have</l>
                     <l>As doe thy Statutes Love,</l>
                     <l>No danger ſhall their quiet ſtate,</l>
                     <l>Impaire or once remove.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>The Support.</head>
                  <p>MY Lord! When in my young years, the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy infinite mercies, had penetrated my heart. I confeſs there was with it, an earneſt deſire, in me to doe or ſuffer ſomething, whereby I might<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> manifeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> my love to thy Majeſty, for thoſe great unexpreſſable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours that thou haſt deigned to beſtow on me thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſervant. But then had I no other thoughts in me, but that if the contrary Religion (which then too much abounded) had prevail'd, I then might have offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up my life in flames, with devotion to manifeſt my love to thee: But now thou haſt turn'd the tide, and art pleas'd to ſuffer two great powers to riſe, both pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing to maintain the truth of our Religion, ſo that now thou haſt taken off my thoughts for ſuffering ſo for thy ſake, but thou haſt put me on another: My Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I will not ſay worſe for me: for whatſoever is done by thee, with me or by me: I am confident, it is the beſt and fitteſt for me, though death to ſome ſpirits be eaſier to bear then reproachfull ſpeeches: And I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe with impatience heretofore did my unruly Spirit, deteſt reproachfull words, and thought a religious death far better: For my Lord, thou knoweſt what reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and ſlanderous ſpeeches they are ſubject to, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe thy name, or declare thy mercies to them.</p>
                  <p>But let them now ſpeak, and in their ſpeech, declare
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169720:41"/> their little love to thee my Lord, and their malice and ſpite to thy children, thou ſhalt ſet my ſpirit beyond the reach of their contempt, where with a holy contempt with thee, I ſhall laugh ſuch fools to ſcorne. And now I dare not ſay, I am an ignorant woman, and unfit to write, for if thou wilt declare thy goodneſs, and thy mercy by weak and contemptible means, who can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt thy will. My gracious God, I will be now ſo farre from being unwilling to doe it, that I will not reſt till I have done it, for in all ages thou wilt not leave thy ſelfe without a witneſſe of thy mercy and goodneſſe to thy children, and therefore I will ſend out my words to ſpeak thy praiſe, and as thou haſt made them comfort to ſome troubled mindes, ſo I wiſh they may be to more, when they ſhall ſee the truth of thy mercifull dealing with me, and how thou haſt made me ſo happy in this world, as my heart can wiſh; for thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me my hearts deſire, and haſt fulfil'd the requeſt of my lipps; for there is not that thing in the world that I can deſire more, then what thou haſt given to me. For long ſince, my Lord, when thou hadſt given me ſence to ſee, that no earthly thing though never ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent or pleaſing could give us a perfect contentment, then made I my prayer to thy divine Majeſty, that thou wouldſt be pleaſed to give me that which the world could not give; and though I confeſſe I did then think it was unpoſſible ever to poſſeſſe a true content in this world, yet my dear Father, I muſt now aske thee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for thoſe miſdoubting thoughts; for I have ſeen thou canſt give us a joy, and a true content, beyond the expreſſion of our ſouls, in this world; for when we poſſeſſe thee with, and in thy creatures, we injoy a feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city that fils our hearts with an unexſpreſſable delight; My Lord! when thou art pleaſed to manifeſt thy ſelfe unto our ſouls, thou bringeſt all that can be deſired. Death that to ſome natures, the mention of it is bitter;
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169720:42"/> to thine, thou mak'ſt it a pleaſing companion, and with paine thou makeſt them pleas'd and happy, and for the bitter ſpeeches of the world, which thy children muſt heare, thou mak'ſt us to forget or contemne them.</p>
                  <p>I muſt confeſſe to thy honour, my great King, that thou makeſt me not to remember the bitterneſſe of this life, thou anſwering me with ſuch joyes in my heart, and thus wilt thou at length, my gracious God, bleſſe all thy children that with an upright minde, and a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere heart, doe earneſtly ſeek their happineſſe alone in thee, and not from the world.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>PSALME 85. 10.</bibl>
                     <q>The Perfume.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>IN thee moſt bleſſed Prince, are thoſe two excellent ingredients mix'd, which yeeld ſo ſweet a ſent to the world, that no corrupted aire of our unſavoury e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy is able to diſperſe. Thy moſt bleſſed body, the ſweeteſt and trueſt perfume that ever proceeded out of the earth, was joyn'd with the odoriferous ſcent of righteouſneſſe from heaven. Bleſſed <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> knew thy perfect body needed no imbalming; That pure Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam that came from heaven at the beginning, kept thy precious body from corruption.</p>
                  <p>On the croſſe was all that that was to be ſuffered in the body, finiſhed, God would not ſuffer his holy one to ſee corruption; truth made haſt, and ſprung the third day from the earth, and righteouſneſs ſhewed her ſelfe from heaven; in thee met mercy and truth, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and peace there kiſſed each other. Now are
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169720:42"/> they in thee conjoyn'd never againe to be ſeparated. 'Tis not for ignorant man, ſeeing thou haſt not reveal'd it, to examine what thou didd'ſt with thy precious ſoul, when thy body was in the grave. My Lord! I will not ſearch into thoſe ſecrets, kept in thine owne Cabinet: Thou haſt reveal'd enough to confirme my faith, and to make me happy. Thou haſt told me, That righteouſneſſe looked downe from heaven; I will not expect thy coming from any other place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>The Acknowledgement.</head>
                  <p>MY Omnipotent God, faine would I ſay ſomething to thee, but I am afraid. But ſhall my woman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh fear make thee looſe thy glory; My God it muſt not! Thy glory muſt ſo dazle mine eyes, that I muſt not regard the cenſure of the world.</p>
                  <p>And if thou, O all-ſeeing eye! ſeeſt ought of my ſelfe, in what I write or ſay, reſtraine my hand from writing, and my tongue from ſpeaking; but if thy glory be the intention of my heart, let not my hand and tongue be aſham'd to confeſſe that I cannot but ſee thoſe infinite bleſſings that thou haſt beſtowed on me, which thou haſt not as yet beſtowed on all. My Lord! I were a fool if I did not ſee them; I were a beaſt if I did not acknowledge them; but thou haſt taught me to know the onely true God, and <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> whom thou haſt ſent into the world, to take away my ſins; this wiſdome given me by thee, inlightens mine eyes to ſee thy bleſſings, and that I muſt not be like a beaſt which receives many favours from thee, without acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Then with infinite thankes I doe acknowledge to thy glory, thou haſt inriched me with a multitude of thy bleſſings.</p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:169720:43"/>
                  <p>And that I may know, that whatſoever is in me ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to good, is from thee: there are times that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee any thing that hath any appearance of good in me; for when, by thy mercies, I lay me down in peace to take my reſt, being happy in the conſideration of thy infinite mercies, and full of thy goodnes; yet in my fleep I finde my thoughts buſied in nothing but a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of confuſed follies, and vaine imaginations, which plainly repreſent to me my naturall condition; that by nature I cannot think a good thought; but thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring thy mercies in the morning againe, reſtoreſt to me thy gifts and graces in which I was happy the night before; So that thou makeſt me to lye downe in peace, and to riſe with joy, when I ſee that thou doſt each day renue to me thy heavenly gifts, for thou art to me as thou art to all that fear thee, the light of my eyes, the joy of my heart, and a Crowne of glory to my head.</p>
                  <p>My Lord! ſhall not theſe bleſſings of thine be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by me, to thy praiſe and glory? for fear the world ſhould ſay, I were proud of them: Moſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple glory in ſomething or other, and thou haſt ſaid, Let them that glory, glory in the Lord. My God! thou haſt heard my prayer, that I leanrt of thy fervant, that thou wouldſt give me a glorying heart, and now thou makeſt me with him to rejoyce in the God of my Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. My Lord! experience hath taught me to know, that if I delight in earthly things, thou wilt take them from me; for thou wilt not have thy children delight in any thing more then in thy ſelfe. But if we love thee thou wilt manifeſt thy ſelfe to us, and wilt give us more full poſſeſſion of thy deſired ſelfe. But my beloved Lord, if after the expreſſion of my exceſſive joy, for being thine, I ſhall through the frailty of mine owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and thy ſufferance fall into any great tranſgreſſion, to make thee for a while to withdraw from me, the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169720:43"/> and joyfull light of thy countenance. My tender Father, aſſure me that thou wilt againe reſtore me to the joy of thy ſalvation here in this world, or thou wilt in thy mercy take me to a more full poſſeſſion of thee in the felicity of thy choſen, where I ſhall perpetually rejoyce with thy children. But to make me carefull of my ſelfe, let me remember thy warning, <hi>Let him tha thinketh he ſtandeth take heed leſt he fall.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>The invincible Souldier.</head>
                  <p>MY Lord, the Lord of Hoſts; I being in ſweet ſecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rity under thy banner, cannot but acknowledge with thankes thy mercy to me, for the meanes that brought me to this felieity. Thou art mercifull to me in letting me be borne of Parents, who were liſted under thy command, and to be brought up by her that did ſurvive, who knew thy ſervice was perfect freedom. She that was happy in being a Souldier of thine, uſed her authority by love, to bring her children under the obedience of that Generall, whom ſhe ſerv'd, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o make me love him in my child-hood, whom her experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence had taught to love and admire; inforc'd me to read his Royall ſtory, wherein I might ſee his victorio us conqueſt, who was neverfoil'd. There did I ſee his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies had all their forces from him, wherewithall they reſiſted him. His wiſdome, his power, his valour, ſtole into my heart a little deſire to follow him. But when I came to conſider what a great Prince I ſhould ſerve, what impenetrable weapons and armour he had provided for me to defend my ſelf, what rewards he had promis'd to give to all that did overcome; I began to contemn the thoughts of ſerving any but that victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince of glory. And ſeeing grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God, thou haſt
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:169720:44"/> bid us take that impenetrable armour. I will not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ever goe without it. Then dear Prince beſtow on me the Girdle of Truth, and put on me the breſt-plate of thy Righteouſnes, and let my feet be ſhod with the Goſpel of peace, and let me have the ſhield of Faith, and ſet on my head the Helmet of Salvation, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct me how to weild the Sword of the Spirit, and when I am ſo arm'd, I ſhall not fear the fiery darts of the aſſailing enemies, Though they be principalities, and powers and rulers of darknes in this world; My Prince whom I ſerve, is a Ruler of thoſe Rulers, and will aſſiſt me: yea the ſtars ſhall aid us in their courſes againſt our adverſaries. That bright morning ſtar ſhall ariſe on our ſide, to enlighten us, and to dazle and afright our weak-ſighted reſiſters, with his exceeding brightneſs. The ſweet influence that flows from that over-ruling ſtar ſhall make us to renew our ſtrength, each houre to maintaine the battail: his gracious aſpect will make all his fighting Souldiers victorious Conquerors, and at the length he will take them up into a Triumphant chariot of glory, to raigne with him as Kings in his Kingdome of immortall felicity, where he will place on their head a Crown of eternall glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>On ECCLES. 9. 7.</bibl>
                     <q>Goe eat thy bread with joy, &amp;c.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>MY Dear Lord! with what a ſweet and pleaſing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject this morning haſt thou preſented mine eyes, that they may deliver it to my heart, for to my heart, thou art pleas'd to ſpeak it, and if any ſhall aske if that meſſage was ſent to me, I will aver it was, for they who
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:169720:44"/> by the hand of faith lay hold on the promiſes of God, are and ſhall be partakers of thoſe promiſes; My hand preſented that object to mine eyes, mine eyes delivered it to my heart, my heart took hold of it by the hand of faith; ſo that I may confidently ſay, It belongs both to Soul and body; And now methinks I hear my God ſaying to me, Go, But ſome may ſay, Goe is a word of ſeparation, and ſo he will ſay to thoſe that ſhall for ever be debar'd of his happy preſence: but yet to me he ſayes, Go, but it is not from him, but with him, to that bleſſed place from which <hi>Adam</hi> fell; and I am ſure it is not from him, but with him; for from him is hell, but here is joy and gladneſſe to my heart, and delicacy of cloathing, and in his preſence is the fulneſſe of joy and at his right hand is life everlaſting. But did I ſay it is to that place from which <hi>Adam</hi> fell; my thoughts then hover'd too neer the earth; it is to heaven my God bids me goe with him; for I muſt eat my bread with joy, and drink my wine with a merry heart, and let my garments be alwayes white, and my head muſt want no odoriſerous oyntment, for God accepts thy workes.</p>
                  <p>My Lord! When I conſider that thoſe words were ſpoken to thoſe whoſe works thou accepteſt: My confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is ſomewhat ſhaken; whether or no thoſe words were ſpoken to me, for thou art a God of pure eyes, and canſt not behold iniquity. I am a creature unclean, defil'd with originall and actuall ſin. How then canſt thou O God accept my workes, for unclean hands de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file what they touch.</p>
                  <p>But ſtagger not my ſoul, nor doubt; for now to my memory is preſented, that to the houſe of <hi>David</hi> was a fountain ſet open, for ſin, and for uncleanneſſe: Haſt thee thither my ſoul, that thou m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſt be clean, for thou needſt not doubt, but that fountain belongs to thee; for from eternity by election wert thou affianc'd to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169720:45"/> him, that was to be the immortall ſon of <hi>David,</hi> and ſo thou being of his linage, the priviledge of that fountain muſt belong to thee: yea my Soule, thou haſt heard himſelfe cry out; If any thirſt let him come to him and drinke, and out of him ſhall flow rivers of living wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  <p>I wil not ſtay, but will haſt and run to thee O bleſſed fountain of life, and I will drinke abundantly of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired water, that ſhall make me capable of ſo great a bliſſe, and purge me clean from my actuall and originall pollutions, ſo that my God may accept my works, and I goe with confidence to eat my bread and drinke my wine with a merry heart.</p>
                  <p>But ſtay my Soul! doſt thou thinke to run to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in a full career of felicity and pleaſure; thou canſt not but remember that the ſervants of God, have eaten the bread of affliction, and drunke the wine of aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and mingled their drinke with their tears; this was their portion heretofore; I confeſſe it was ſo, but I finde in this meſſage at (now) which cals to my minde that there was a time when I could not do ſo; for when I lay polluted in the deformity of my ſins, and had my hands foul with the poiſon of mine iniquities; 'tis no wonder, if then our bread be the bread of affliction, and our wine the wine of aſtoniſhment, and how can we chuſe but mingle our drinke with our tears, when we feed our ſelves with thoſe hands which we have waſht in poiſon? how can we chuſe but thinke that that bread muſt end us here, and carry us from a fearfull life in this world to be tormented in a hideous place of miſery for ever.</p>
                  <p>O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y God! How can they either eat or drink with contentment, who have not firſt ſought out that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine wherein they may waſh themſelves clean from that dreadfull poiſon: But my Soul, I have heard thee ſay, thou wouldſt haſt to that pure ſtream, and waſh thee
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169720:45"/> cleane from thine iniquities, and thou being clean, maiſt now goe and poſſeſſe thoſe free liberties.</p>
                  <p>My Soul, Thou muſt now flee to heaven, and there eat that living bread, and drinke that wine of life, which cannot be taken but with exceſſive joy, ſo that out of them ſhall flow rivers of living waters; ſprings of joy ſhall riſe in thee, and ſtreams of thanks and praiſe ſhall flow from thee, to thy dear God, for his infinite bleſſings; theſe will be to thee rivers of life.</p>
                  <p>And from heaven my ſoul maiſt thou take thoſe white garments with which thou maiſt always be cloath'd, for his garments were white and gliſtering: then aske for thoſe robes of purity that are his, for thou maiſt be ſure thou ſhalt obtaine; and being cloath'd in thoſe gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thou needſt not fear thou ſholdſt ever be found naked or unſeemly dreſt, for thou ſhalt be gloriouſly habited, becauſe God will make thy righteouſnes in him as clear as the light, and thy juſt dealing as the noon day; and now my Soul thou loving and deſiring thoſe garments of righteouſneſſe, needſt not fear that thy head ſhall want any precious ointment; for if thou with and in that great King, loveſt right and hateſt ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; God, even thy God will annoint thee with the oyle of gladnes.</p>
                  <p>And now my Soul, Thou ſeeſt the priviledges that are preſented to thee in this ſpeech: but thou ſaidſt ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while, it belonged to thy body too; I confeſſe it did, but my thoughts were ſo taken up with the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the infinite felicity of my Soul, that I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt forgot my body; and truly did not ſhe accord to the action of my Soul, and deſire with her onely to be happy by the priviledges that adhere to her by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my Soul, I would never ſeek to content her, nor regard any priviledges that belongs to her, but ſhe is an aſſenting companion to my Soul, and an inſtrument to convey the promiſes of God to her, and ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169720:46"/> be a perfect glorious companion with her in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall bliſſe, I will now regard the priviledges that belong to her in this meſſage: And though I thought that place from which <hi>Adam</hi> fell too mean for the felicity of my Soul, yet for my body it is a place ſufficiently conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable; and ſeeing the benefits that were loſt by the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> are all, with many more reſtor'd to thee by the ſecond: My body, thou maiſt goe with my Soul, and eat thy temporall bread with joy, and drinke thy wine with a merry heart, and thy garments may be pleaſant and delighting, and thy head want no odorife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ointment, for our bountiful and liberall God, hath given us many creatures for pleaſure and delight, as well as for neceſſity; but 'tis with a reſtraint, our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are of <hi>Adams</hi> race, we muſt not touch that which is forbidden; thou maiſt uſe them all with an innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, not with any ſiniſter end, or to thinke to make thy ſelfe like a God, by them or with them; but thou maiſt lawfully uſe them all to praiſe thy God, for them and with them.</p>
                  <p>Thus my body, thou ſeeſt thou art happy with my Soule, and my Soul is happy in thee, and you ſhall be both glorious together in Heaven; and now my heart can wiſh no greater bliſſe on earth, but my tongue muſt ever ſay,</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To my Great God all glory bee,</l>
                     <l>That gives ſuch bleſſings unto me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:169720:46"/>
                  <head>Ambition.</head>
                  <p>MY Lord, I will not winely deſire to pry into thy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet of ſecrets, to finde out what was the reaſon, why thou didſt caſt down thoſe ſometime bright Angels in Heaven, now tormenting &amp; tormented ſpirits in hel; but I have heard that ſome have thought that it was for having too ambitious and too high deſires.</p>
                  <p>My Lord! Could their deſires be rais'd higher then are mine? for I confeſſe mine reach unto thy Throne; Nothing will now ſatisfie me, but to be inthron'd with thee in glory. I am grown ſo confident too, that I aver thoſe high deſires in me to be lawfull, and know that for them thou wilt not caſt me from thee, but wilt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne me with thee,</p>
                  <p>My Lord! I ſee 'tis dangerous to doe any thing in thy ſervice without a command, or a meſſage from thee: For I ſee many things done by thy command, bleſt with felicity, when without, puniſht with miſery. I finde no command given them for ſuch deſires; but methinkes I hear that bleſt Apoſtle of thine, when returned from his heavenly rapture, cals to me, and tels me from thee, that I muſt ſeek thoſe things that are above, where Chriſt ſits at the right hand of God, and that my life is hid in Chriſt with thee: ſo that now I ſeeking to attaine my high deſires, made lawfull by thy command, am not onely placed on thy Throne, by thee, but I am in thee; and thoſe rebellious Spirits that ſought to obtain their ambitious deſires, without thy commands, are not onely caſt out of thy bleſſed preſence, but alſo are for ever to be tormented in eternall miſery.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:169720:47"/>
                     <l>Now on thy Throne thou haſt plac'ſt me,</l>
                     <l>Great God with thee,</l>
                     <l>No greater bliſſe can wiſhed be,</l>
                     <l>My Lord by me.</l>
                     <l>I now will ſet me downe and reſt</l>
                     <l>Being ſo high bleſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>MY God! I will not doe good on earth to ſhine with thee in glory: But becauſe I will ſhine with thee in glory, I will doe good on earth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon Peters denyall.</head>
                  <p>SAint <hi>Peter!</hi> How well had it been, hadſt thou ſpoke and kept thy word; for why ſhouldſt thou be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at thy good Maſter; he telling thee that himſelfe ſhould be ſmitten, you ſhould but be ſcattered: Had he told you that you ſhould be ſmitten, and he ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from you, there might have been ſome reaſon, you might have been offended; but when himſelfe was to be ſmitten, and for your ſakes too, to ſecure you from eternall deſtruction; Methinks the offence was taken on the contrary ſide. But if in thy family, it was ſo taken, thou ſtrict Prince of perfection, no wonder if it be ſo in families of looſer libertie, and full of imperfection. I doe not wonder to hear thee ſay, Thou wilt not be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, but I wonder that thou wert not over-joyed to hear him telling thee, that for all he ſhould ſo ſuffer, yet he would after he was riſen, goe before you into
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169720:47"/> 
                     <hi>Galilee.</hi> Methinks, I ſhould hear you filling the world with ſongs of thanks-giving, for joy of that Kingdome he hath promiſed you, from his Father, and for the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance he gave you of his reſurrection; rather then hear thee denying ſuch a powerfull and loving Maſter, with Oathes. My Lord! Let me, with him, not be aſhamed to profeſſe thee; but keep me from the ſhame of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying thee, or if thou maiſt gain glory by my fall, give me with him, abundance of teares, and a heart and tongue to confeſſe my fault to thee, and to the world, that thou and they may ſee with him, my repentance.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>My Redemption acknowledged.</head>
                  <p>MY Lord! Haſt thou ſpoken it, and ſhall it not be performed? It is impoſſible? Thou the Ruler of all the world, haſt by thy bleſſed Prophet, bid, that they which are redeemed by the Lord, declare with praiſe, how he hath redeemed them from the hand of the oppreſſor, rather then thy word ſhould not be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil'd to thy faithful friend; Thou vvilt raiſe him children out of the duſt of the earth, rather then this command not be performed, thou vvilt raiſe me who am as one out of the duſt to be one of them, that muſt declare vvith praiſe, hovv thou haſt delivered me from the hands of mine enemies. And though I finde it a thing now adays done but by few; and ſo by doing it, may make my ſelf a wonder, and ridiculous to the world, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther womaniſh reaſons, that might detaine me from it; yet I cannot but know thou haſt redeemed me, and I muſt confeſſe, it was thou alone, my great God, that haſt done it, for it was none but the great God, and Ruler of the world, that could deliver me out of the hands of that great enemy of mine, and of all man kind;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169720:48"/> that Prince that rules in the aire, who goes about like a roaring Lyon, ſeeking each minute to devour us: Out of the arms and power of that fiery enemy, haſt thou unparalel'd Conqueror delivered me, elſe had I been led captive to his will; For that great deliverance of thine, my Soul ſhall render thee continuall praiſe: It was thou, O great Prince of life and death, that trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed over death, thou only canſt deliver me from the feare of death, and make me imbrace it with a Heaven of contentment. It is onely thou my Lord, who alone doſt ariſe to them that fear thy name, with healing in thy wings, canſt, and haſt cur'd me of, (to man) uncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable diſeaſes. Thou haſt cur'd me too of the plague of my own heart.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No Conqueror did Conquer ought,</l>
                     <l>But o're what Death had power,</l>
                     <l>Thou Conqueror haſt Conquer'd Death,</l>
                     <l>Which Conquer'd us each houre.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>PSALME</bibl>
                     <q>Thou haſt compaſt me about with Songs of Deliverance.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>BLeſſed King! Well maiſt thou ſay, Thou ſhouldſt be compaſt about with Songs of deliverance, when the Lord of Hoſts was thy hiding place; with him are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Complainers; in his preſence is nothing but joy; thoſe that are under the protection of his pleaſant wings, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but have their hearts full of exceſſive joy, which
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169720:48"/> moves their tongues to ſing ſongs of praiſes and thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving to their great and powerfull protector for deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering them out of all their troubles; needs muſt thou be compaſſed about with Songs of delight, thou couldſt not chuſe but ſing thy Self too, thoſe Songs thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt teach to thy chief Singers; that they might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe thee in the ſweet aire of delighting praiſes, and with thee my Soule muſt deſire to ſing, when with thee I am ſo protected.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Saint Stephen.</head>
                  <p>GOd can make our faces to ſhine like Angels to daunt our enemies; and he here can make us to ſee his face to ſhine in glory, to comfort our Souls: Why then ſhould we fear our fierceſt enemies; why then ſhould we not be confident of the aide of our loving and powerfull God.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thy bleſſed power is like thy Light,</l>
                     <l>But our frail fear is like our night.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>MY Soul being plac'ſt on the wings of contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with them raiſes me to the Regions of feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>The foundation and felicity.</head>
                  <p>MY great God! Thou that haſt aided me in laying the foundation of aſſurance, aſſiſt me ſtill now towring
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169720:49"/> in the turrets of contentment; and ſet all know, that they can never with ſafety aſcend the turrets of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting contentment; if they have not firſt laid the true foundation of aſſurance.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Temptation of the doubting of Heaven.</head>
                  <p>MY Soul! Though that ſubtle enemy of thine, and of all men, doe ſeek to ſeduce thee, by his inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting perſwaſions, to doubt of that unexpreſſable and immortall felicity of thy Soul and body: yet my Soule, faint not! For if the holy Writ be true, thy felicity is certaine; the which my gracious God I doe moſt confidently believe, to be the written word of the God of all the world, by whoſe word and will, I, and this Fabrick were created; though that pernicious enemy, ſeeks to perſwade me that it is a fancy of a ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious braine, and writ to keep people in awe to human obedience. And becauſe nothing doth pleaſe our Souls, but the thoughts of eternall bliſſe, nor afright them, but the dread of eternall puniſhment, therefore have they fained a heaven for reward of the vertuous, and a hell for puniſhment of the diſobedient; and that thoſe felicities, of which I have written, are but fictions of my owne braine, and ſomewhat like they that invented it, and partly taken out of it.</p>
                  <p>But my gracious God, keep me, that I fall not by theſe temptations, but let me know why he is, and hath been ſo buſie in drawing me to doubt of thy being, and of that glorious heaven, which I do notwithſtanding his temptations, believe I ſhall poſſeſſe with thee.</p>
                  <p>My God is it to draw me to a looſe liberty of my life,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169720:49"/> and ſo by diſobeying thee, I might live in fear of being caſt out of thy favour to eternall puniſhment? if ſo! I will tell him, that he may ceaſe his labour: for if that which I beleeve to be the holy word of God, be a fancy of any braine, it is ſo juſt and pleaſing to my ſoul, that with all my power and might; I will endeavour to lead my life according to the direction of that exact and roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Law; and ſo hatefull is any thing to me that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it, that when thorow my frailty I doe what in it is forbidden, I am hatefull to my ſelfe, till I am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that that offence be waſhed from me, and that ſomething within me aſſures me, that the breach of that tranſgreſſion, is pardon'd. This is a ſtrong argument to me againſt that temptation, and of the divinity and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of my Soul; for if my Soul were not to be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally either happy or miſerable, why ſhould the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of eternall miſery, trouble me, and the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of eternall bliſſe ſo exceedingly joy me. Tempter goe! Reaſon and experience teacheth us to ſee, that likeneſſe breeds love; our Souls, our minds (for ſuch things there are) can never love nor delight in what is not; but our Souls affect eternall glory, then ſure ſuch a thing there is: but be it ſo, or be it not, ſuch a thing is preſented to our conſideration, and if I am not to live a life of eternall bliſſe hereafter; yet for the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of my preſent life, I will ſo neer as I can run in the paths that lead to that heaven, which I ſo much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that I might live with a confident hope that I ſhall poſſeſſe it, for nothing can truely ſatisfie my Soul, but a heaven of eternity, and with theſe thoughts I can live on earth in a heaven of felicity.</p>
                  <p>Tempter! Thou art like to looſe thy labour, for I muſt take up that reſolution, not to live a ſenſuall and vicious life; for if I have no grace; ſuch a life is hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to my diſpoſition, and ſuch a life would not I live, were there no God to give bleſſedneſſe, Devil to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169720:50"/> torment. But one thing more I have now to tell thee; I in the Sanctuary of the great God of all the world, preſenting my petitions to him, that by ſomething I might be aſſur'd that thy wicked ſuggeſtions to make me doubt of his being, were falſe, I was directed to conſider the glorious Sun, which then ſhined bright in mine eyes; ſo that I plainly ſee, that great God, of whoſe being thou wouldſt have me doubt, doth aid and aſſiſt me againſt thy wicked temptations: for it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be but a great God, that can make and governe ſo glorious and ſo great a light, the God that made that, made me; that God I did offend in my firſt parents, and ſince in my owne perſon, but to him am recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled in his firſt borne Son Jeſus Chriſt, who is God and man, and for his ſake ſhall I poſſeſſe a Kindome of feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city here, and at the laſt a Kingdome of eternall glory.</p>
                  <closer>To him be Glory.</closer>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>On the Sun-riſing.</head>
                  <p>AS the appearance of the Sun-beams, diſperſeth the clouds of darkneſs, which brings ſadneſs to the earth: ſo let the bright ſhining beams of thy Spirit, O heavenly Son of light diſperſe the clouds of darke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing thoughts and vaine imaginations, the which do darken the brightneſs of my Soul, and bring ſadneſs to my heart. Let them purifie and raiſe my minde, that I may ſtill be ſinging praiſe, and let me ever ſay.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To my great God all glory be,</l>
                     <l>Who makes his light to ſhine on me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:169720:50"/>
                  <head>Heaven upon Earth.</head>
                  <p>MY Lord! Though thou wilt not take me from earth to live in Heaven with thee; yet thou comming from heaven to live on earth with me, makes me on earth to live in heaven with thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>The Temple.</head>
                  <p>MY God! Is my body the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt? What Palace can there be in this ſmall Fabrick, fit to entertaine ſo great a Prince; yet thou haſt ſaid, If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ny love thee, thy Father will love them, and thou, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ee, and thy holy ſpirit, which cannot be ſeparated from thee, will come and make thy abode with him. My Lord and King! thou knoweſt I love thee, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ong ſince I was willing to have left the world, and all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he bleſſings that thou haſt given me in it, to have gone to live with thee: but what talke I, leaving the world to come to live with thee. Thou art come into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he world to live with mee and in me. But my great Lord, where in me, ſhall I finde thee; haſt thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hron'd thy ſelfe in my heart, give me then thy aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce, that no proud imagination, for my own greatnes, may ariſe to diſinthrone thee, and make the diſtaſte that habitation; but be thou in my heart, ever atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by ſweet humility and humble obedience. Let all the members of my body be imployed in thy ſervice; Let my hands adminiſter to thy Saints, and not ſtretcht out to covetouſneſſe. Let my feet be ſwift to run in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he wayes of thy commandements, and not to ſhed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ocent blood: or if in my head thou haſt taken up thy
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169720:51"/> ſeat, there let humility attend on thee too, or I ſhall fear thou wilt goe from me; for thou reſiſteſt the proud: but though thou beeſt high, and inſtabiteſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, yet thou, O great Prince will dwell with the humble. Then in my head, and in all that belong to it doe thou finde humble obedience, that there I might retaine thee. Let not mine eyes have any proud look nor be windows to lett in vanity, but let them be ever looking to the hils from whence cometh my ſalvation. Let not my tongue which thou haſt given me to ſerve thee, be imployed to back-bite or defame any the leaſt of thy children, or any one; for how know I who are thine, or who not, but let my tongue be ever ſpeaking to thy praiſe and glory; and let the words of mouth be accprable in thy ſight; nor let mine ears liſten to any idle or unſeemly diſcourſe, that may diſpleaſe thy divine Majeſty, and let my noſtrils be ever filled with the ſweet ſavour that comes from thy heavenly gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: So if all the faculties of my body be imployed by my Soul, humbly to ſerve thee, I ſhall live and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe a glorying heart, becauſe I know this body is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Temple of the Deity.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then where I am a Heaven muſt be,</l>
                     <l>For thou doſt bring a Heaven with thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>The true Object of Love.</head>
                  <p>MY Lord! When thou wert pleas'd to take my thoughts quite off from the world, I was directed to regard that place, where thou bidſt us ceaſe from man, for wherein is he to be accounted of, for his breath is in his noſtrils, yet he a creature after thine owne i<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mage, and the excellenteſt of all thy workman ſhip or earth yet this rare creature, his love, his hatred not to be regarded, for thou canſt in an inſtant take away that
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:169720:51"/> thin fume of life, and then what power hath he to love or hate. My Lord! He is indeed a moſt contemptible creature in reſpect of thee. But when my Soul enters into the conſideration of thy greatneſſe and deep a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſſe of thy endleſſe power and mercy. My Soul is ſtruck dumbe, and knows not what to ſay, but ſilence giving me opportunity to conſider of thy infinite love to me, power, forme, beauty and excellency, in, and about thee; my Soul is wounded with a deep affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee, and love cannot, will not be ſilent: And now my great and powerfull God, was it not enough for thee, to make ſo great and beautifull a ſtructure for me, and for all men; but when I had run from thee, by my diſobedience into the territories and torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arms of my enemy, for thee, O moſt glorious Prince of eternall bliſſe, to leave thy Kingdome where thou wert attended by a multitude of bright Angels, and bleſſed Saints, which continually ſing thy praiſes with their heavenly voices; for thee to leave ſuch tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent delights, to take on thee my frail fleſh, and come to me, and ſubject thy ſelfe to all the contempts that an inſulting enemy could impoſe: had not this been enough to have manifeſted an unanſwerable love to ſo contemptible a creature, but thou, My dear Prince I who wouldeſt ſet a perfect patterne of humility and love, for all that were thine to follow for love to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, thou wert content to dye, and the moſt painfull and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious death that could be inflicted on the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt perſon: Thou who wert ſerv'd by all the world, was pleas'd thus to ſerve for me, and to dye, to ſave me from eternall death; and before I knew into what torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing habitation I had plung'd my ſelfe by my rebellion, thou wert pleas'd to declare to me how thou hadſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem'd me out of thoſe moſt cruel inthralments, by thy willingly yeelding to dye for me; for none could have power, O great Prince of Heaven and earth, to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169720:52"/> have taken away thy life, hadſt thou not laid it downe of thine owne accord thou wert pleaſe to tell me too, though I live here among thy enemies and mine, yet I ſhould not be afraid of them, for they can but kill my body, and that too not without thy leave, for none can take thy children out of thy hand, unleſſe thou art pleas'd to deliver them into the hand of their perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and by that fiery Chariot to convey us to that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall Kingdome, which thou haſt promiſed to thoſe that beleeve on thee; where we ſhall receive from thy hand the beautifull Crowne of our eternall glory. O my God! Who can chuſe but be raviſht with thy unfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom'd mercy, and unexpreſſable love to thy poor, yet by thee inriched creatures. My dear Prince! What ſhall I doe, to let all the world know what engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments my Soul hath to thee. I do wiſh it were in my power, as in my deſires, that all the world may ſing Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lalujahs to thee for the ſaving of my Soul from that cruel adverſary, and for the glory that thou wilt inveſt her in, and that they would ſing publick praiſes unto thee, for thy mercies to themſelves too: would tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> were their imployment, then ſhould not thy ſervice be ſo much ſlighted, nor thy name ſo much diſhonoured nor thy ſervants ſo much contemn'd; But</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let them ſing praiſes to thy name,</l>
                     <l>Whom thou haſt bleſt,</l>
                     <l>And kept their Souls from endleſſe paine</l>
                     <l>And plac'ſt in reſt.</l>
                     <l>Thou haſt me kept from helliſh paine,</l>
                     <l>And plac'ſt in reſt.</l>
                     <l>How can I chuſe but praiſe thy name</l>
                     <l>When I'me ſo bleſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:169720:52"/>
                  <head>Rom. 12. 1.</head>
                  <p>MY Lord! I cannot plead ignorance, for I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe I have often read it, and knew that I was to offer up my ſelf a living ſacrifice to thy Majeſty, and to give my ſelfe wholly to thy diſpoſing, and not to have any ſequeſtred thoughts from thee, dedicated to mine own ends, in either my actions, words or thoughts: but my dear Father, I now plainly ſee the neceſſity of entring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nto thy Courts, to hear thee, moſt gracious Prince ſpeake to us by thy Embaſſadors; And I, nor any other ought to ſay; what ſhould I go thither, to hear a man tell me, but what I knew before? But my Lord, thy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances are powerful, and thou workeſt more effectually on our hearts for the moſt part, by the preaching of thy word from them, then by our own reading and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and now I begin to ſuſpect, I have not offered up my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elfe ſo exactly to thee, as I ſhould; for me thought, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e beſought me from thee, to offer up my ſelf a living ſacrifice, wholly and acceptably to thee, My Lord! I have heretofore long ſince given my ſelfe to thee by piece meals; but I fear, reſerving ſomething from thee, and if offering my ſelfe wholly to thee, be but a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oble ſerving of thee, ſure when I reſerved any thing from thee, that ſervice was contemptible: But graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Father, pardon all that heretofore I have done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe in thy ſervice, for now I doe give up my ſelfe wholly to thee; But how ſhall I dare to ſay my ſelf, I dare not appeare by my ſelfe in thy preſence, yet with, and in my ſelf I may; Thou haſt taught me out of thy royall ſtory, to know that thou haſt given me that Princely Son of thine, I cannot chuſe but accept ſo rich a preſent; then ſeeing he is mine, and I am his, I am confident to preſent my ſelfe to thee, with and in
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:169720:53"/> him; My Lord, thou canſt not but take the care <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> me, now I have given my ſelfe wholly to thee; the gracious Father let me live without fear of falling fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thee; for if I fall from thee, wilt not thou looſe pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of thy glory? My Lord, I know it ſtands not wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thine honour to let that periſh which is committed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to thy hands; then ſith I have commited my ſelf who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to thee, let me with confidence ſit downe and reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ar no evill,</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For from all ill I ſhall be free,</l>
                     <l>Sure nothing can be ill to me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon Adams fall.</head>
                  <p>MY Dear God! did thy Majeſty make <hi>Adam</hi> wiſe before he fell, then any man; or haſt thou ſinc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his fall given man the gift of Faith, or had he no nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Faith, or did <hi>Adam</hi> not beleeve thee the maker <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> all things, ſo much as we beleeve each other? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Adam</hi> did not beleeve thee, when thou toldſt him th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the day he ſhould eat of that tree, he ſhould dye th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> death. We thinke men wiſe when they avoid what told them will hurt them. I finde <hi>Adam</hi> not ſo wiſe and if one tell us, Mercury will cauſe our death, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that are called the depraved Sons of <hi>Adam,</hi> will not ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it, if we be in our right ſenſes, though the pureneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the colour may tempt us, and it be onely a morta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> man that tels us ſo, who neither made it, nor eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> try'd it. <hi>Adam</hi> beleev'd not the O Lord, who made that tree, and gaveſt the nature to it; O <hi>Adam,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> made thee to eat of that tree, hadſt thou not this great world full of all pleaſures to content thee, a beauti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> healthfull active body, a minde indued with all exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and pleaſing knowledge: No where couldſt tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> caſt thine eye but it had pleaſing objects: nothin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:169720:53"/> couldſt thou taſt, but it was delicious; no troubled mind, no diſtracted thoughts, to take thee one minute, from theſe delights, or cauſe thee to wiſh a change. Oh what then was it? But now I muſt check my ſelfe; Great God pardon me, I now ſin with <hi>Adam,</hi> whiles I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring why <hi>Adam</hi> ſinn'd: he would know what he ſhould not, I what I cannot; Thou hadſt made him ſo wiſe as was ſufficient for any mortall man; and hadſt given him ſuch qualities of his Soul as were requiſite to have made him for ever happy, in that bleſſed condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Frail <hi>Adam,</hi> I will no more examine, whether thou hadſt faith or no, or whether thou didſt thinke to have been happier by what was kept from thee, then in poſſeſſing what was ſo plentifully given to thee.</p>
                  <p>Great God, I will content my ſelf to know thou hadſt made him at firſt in a happy condition, and us ſo in him; and will be patient now I ſee my ſelfe in a worſe: becauſe thou haſt given me faith to beleeve I ſhall be in a better. And as <hi>Adam</hi> made himſelfe unhappy by expecting to be happier; So I ſhall be more happy by beleeving I ſhall be gloriouſly perfect hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Security in Danger.</head>
                  <p>MY Lord! When with that bleſſed ſervant of thine I ſend up to thee my petitions for ſecurity againſt thoſe that riſe up againſt us; Let me receive his aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that thou heareſt me out of thy holy hill, and let me ſay with him, I will lay me downe and alſo ſleep in peace, for thou Lord onely makeſt me dwell in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. I will not be afraid, of ten thouſand of people, that ſhould beſet me round about; for ſeeing it hath pleas'd thee to let me be in a Kingdome of diviſion, though bleſſed be thy name who hath yet preſerv'd me, I am now in a place of peace, yet for ought I know I might to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169720:54"/> morrow be incompaſſed with ten thouſand enemies, though not to me in particular, yet to thoſe among whom I am now in ſafety: But if thou art pleas'd I ſhall be ſo inclos'd, then let not me be afraid of them, fhr thou canſt preſerve me, either by deſtroying thoſe that would harme me, or by letting me finde favour in the ſight of mine enemies, or by their hands canſt thou ſend me to thy bleſſed Tabernacle of ſecurity, where I ſhall never need any more to ſend up prayers for deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, but ſhall alwayes ſing praiſes to thee, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo many wayes to deliver me.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And ſo all fear I now may bid adieu,</l>
                     <l>Goe enemies, I'me ſecur'd from you.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>The Royall Prieſt-hood.</head>
                  <p>PEace! Preſent now no more to me (to take my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit from the height of felicity) that I am a creature of a weaker ſex, a woman. For my God! If I muſt live after the example of thy bleſſed Apoſtle, I muſt live by faith, and faith makes things to come, as preſent; and thou haſt ſaid by thy ſervant, that we ſhall be like thy bleſſed Son: then thou wilt make all thy people as Kings and Prieſts, Kings are men, and men are Kings; And Souls have no ſex; the hidden man of the heart, makes us capable of being Kings; for I have heard it is that within makes the man; then are we by election capable of as great a dignity as any mortall man; But thoughts of mortals! now Adieu; I will cloſe the eyes of my Soul, to mortality, and will not open them but to eternity; ſeeing that by thy grace and faith in thee, thou haſt made us partaker of thy divine nature, by thy aſſiſtance I will live by faith; I will no more
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:169720:54"/> now ſee my ſelf as mortall, but as an immortall King will I begin to live, that hidden man never dies, but when mine immortall King, that plac'ſt me in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of felicity with him; ſhall ſee it fit time, he will raiſe me on a triumphant Chariot, compos'd of the wings of bright Angel, to his immortall Kingdome of Glory, where I ſhall reigne with him for all eternity, and never more deſire to change. Aud as a Royall Prieſt muſt I be to thee; ever offering up the ſweet incenſe of my praiſes to thy divine Majeſty, for thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercies to me, thy unworthy ſervant.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>The ſecure Pavillion.</head>
                  <p>MY God, Thy children need not now pray that thoſe lips may be put to ſilence that ſpeak grievous things againſt them; they have long ſince had a freind, and thou a ſervant, that ſent up his petitions to thee for that, and as if he had been raviſht with a preſent an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer from thee, he cryes out; O how great is thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that thou haſt laid up in ſtore for them that fear thee, before the Sons of men, that would diſhonour thy ſervants. And now he hath brought us ſo pleaſing a meſſage from thee, that it is no wonder if we with diſregard ſlight thoſe unſavory words which we hear. And now look here all you who ſhall any way ſlight or annoy his children, by your odd ſpeeches; they are plac'ſt above your reach, for God will hide them in the ſecret of his preſence, from the pride of men, he will keep them ſecretly in his Pavilion, from the ſtrife of tongues, you may ſhoot, but your aime muſt be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove your head, if you think to hit them, and when you have ſhot, your arrows cannot reach them, but they may light where you would not have them, on your own heads.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:169720:55"/>
                  <head>A Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>MY God! What buſineſſe on earth is worth detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Soul from Heaven, that is prepar'd with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to come from earth, to live in heaven with thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Palmer!</hi> Why told you me, God hath ſomething here remarkable for mee to doe, before I leave the earth; elſe could I have laid downe my head each night, with expectation of a mornings riſe in heaven; now I doe lay it downe onely with a contenting joy, that I am his, and that when his will is done with me, or by me here; I ſhall then goe to poſſeſſe tha Heaven which onely can content the deſire of my immortall Soul: Had you not told me ſo, I might have hop'd, that exceſſive joy, for the glory which I ſhall poſſeſſe, might have rais'd me to that bliſſe to which I doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire. My God, my Soul breaths after thee, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſatisfied, till ſhe comes to a full poſſeſſion of thee.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Lord, what on earth can there be done by mee,</l>
                     <l>Worth keeping here, my longing Soul from thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:169720:55"/>Wings my Doves you have now obtain'd To flee to that Invincible Rock Where you may hide you ſafe In thoſe Clifts of Security From your Malignant Enemies, Who may flee after you. And think to graſpe you, And ſo to hurt you, But they cannot.</q>
               <q>But you may without any gaul tell them, You are plac'd beyond their envies reach, And with that bleſt Apoſtle may ſay 'Tis a ſmall matter for me to be judg'd By you, or of mans judgement The Lord is Judge of all; He judgeth me, and I Am ſafe under His powerfull Wings.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
